<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="default.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The tragedie of Bonduca [Electronic resource]</title>
            <author>Fletcher,  John,  1579-1625</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>creation of machine-readable version</resp>
               <name>Gunby,  D. C. (David Charles)</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>
            <seg type="designation">Text data</seg>
            <seg type="size">(1 file : ca. 119 kilobytes)</seg>
         </extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>[Depositor details removed]<date>1985-03-06</date>
            </authority>
            <distributor>
               <orgName type="OTA">University of Oxford Text Archive</orgName>
               <placeName>Oxford</placeName>
               <address>
                  <orgName type="OTA">University of Oxford Text Archive</orgName>
                  <orgName type="OUCS">Oxford University Computing
          Services</orgName>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">0623</idno>
            <!--New OTA availability statement-->
        <availability n="OTA-new" rend="visible" status="free">
               <p xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
                  seasr:id="600000073">Freely available for non-commercial 
         use provided that this header is included in its 
         entirety with any copy distributed.</p>
            </availability>
            <!--Old Availability-->
      </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="true">Mode of access: Online. OTA website</note>
            <note anchored="true">Title proper taken from beginning of electronic text</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Transcribed from: Comedies and tragedies / written by Francis Beaumont and Iohn Fletcher,  Gentlemen .... -- London : Printed for Humphrey Robinson,  at the three Pidgeons,  and for Humphrey Moseley at the Princes Armes in St Pauls church-Yard,  1647. -- First folio;  includes the plays not hitherto printed,  except the Wild-goose chase,  which was missing,  but recovered and printed in 1652. -- "The Epistle dedicatorie" is signed by John Lowin,  Joseph Taylor,  and eight others;  "To the reader" by Ja. Shirley,  who is usually regarded as the editor.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
               seasr:id="5000000101">Authorship tests</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
               seasr:id="5000000107"/>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
               seasr:id="5000000112">Encoding format: Unknown markup</p>
            <p xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
               seasr:id="5000000115">Text in capital letters</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="SN">Name of scene</tagUsage>
               <tagUsage gi="SSD">Stage direction</tagUsage>
               <tagUsage gi="Q">Speaker</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
               seasr:id="5000000136"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="OTASH">
               <bibl>University of Oxford Text Archive Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date>[198-?]</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#OTASH">
               <term type="genre"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
               <term type="genre">Plays -- England -- 17th century</term>
               <term type="genre">Tragedies -- England -- 17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://www.ota.ox.ac.uk/processing">
               <term type="class">legacy</term>
               <term type="license">Free for non-commercial use</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2000-10-26</date>
            <label>Cataloguer</label>
            <name>Webb,  Anton</name>Header changed in accordance with ISBD(ER) guidelines and expanded. Validated in the TEI Lite DTD using XMetal 2.0
      </change>
         <change>
            <date when="1998-01-14">14 Jan 1998</date>
            <label>cvt (converter)</label>
            <name>Burnard,  Lou</name>Header auto-generated from TOMES
      </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
      
         <head>The Tragedie of Bonduca</head>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="4000000229">
               <head> Actus Primus. Scaena Prima.</head>
            <stage>Enter Bonduca, daughters,  Hengo,  Nennius,  souldiers.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000236">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> the hardy Romanes? O ye gods of Britain, </l>
               <l>the rust of arms, the blushing shame of souldiers; </l>
               <l>are these the men that conquer by inheritance?</l>
               <l>The fortune-makers? These the julians, 
 <stage>Enter Caratach</stage>
               </l>
               <l>that with the sun measure the end of nature, </l>
               <l>making the world but one Rome and one Caesar?</l>
               <l>Shame,  how they flee Caesars soft soul dwells in 'em; </l>
               <l>their mothers got 'em sleeping, pleasure nurst 'em, </l>
               <l>their bodies sweat with sweet oils, loves allurements, </l>
               <l>not lustie arms. Dare they send these to seek us, </l>
               <l>these Romane girls? Is Britain grown so wanton?</l>
               <l>Twice we have beat'em, Nennius, scatter'd 'em, </l>
               <l>and through their big-bon'd germans, on whose pikes</l>
               <l>the honour of their actions sit in triumph, </l>
               <l>made themes for songs to shame 'em, and a woman, </l>
               <l>a woman beat 'em, Nennius; a weak woman, </l>
               <l>a woman beat these Romanes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000294">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> so it seems.</l>
               <l>A man would shame to talk so.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000305">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> who's that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000313">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> i.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000320">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> cousin, do you grieve my fortunes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000327">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> no,  Bonduca, </l>
               <l>if I grieve, 'tis the bearing of your fortunes; </l>
               <l>you put too much winde to your sail: discretion</l>
               <l>and hardie valour art the twins of honour, </l>
               <l>and nurs'd together, make a conquerour:</l>
               <l>divided, but a talker. 'T is a truth, </l>
               <l>that Rome has fled before us twice, and routed; </l>
               <l>a truth we ought to crown the gods for, lady, </l>
               <l>and not our tongues. A truth is none of ours, </l>
               <l>nor in our ends, more then the noble bearing:</l>
               <l>for then it leaves to be a vertue, lady; </l>
               <l>and we that have been victors, beat our selves, </l>
               <l>when we insult upon our honours subject.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000370">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> my valiant cousin, is it foul to say</l>
               <l>what liberty and honour bid us do, </l>
               <l>and what the gods allow us?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000383">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> no, Bonduca, </l>
               <l>so what we say, exceed not what we do.</l>
               <l>Ye call the Romanes fearful, fleeing Romanes, </l>
               <l>and Romane girls, the lees of tainted pleasures:</l>
               <l>does this become a doer? Are they such?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000402">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> they are no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000409">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> where is your conquest then?</l>
               <l>Why are your altars crown'd with wreathes of flowers, </l>
               <l>the beasts with gilt horns waiting for the fire?</l>
               <l>The holy druides composing songs</l>
               <l>of everlasting life to victory?</l>
               <l>Why are these triumphs, lady? For a may-game?</l>
               <l>For hunting a poor herd of wretched Romanes?</l>
               <l>Is it no more? Shut up your temples,  Britains.</l>
               <l>And let the husband-man redeem his heifers; </l>
               <l>put out our holy fires; no timbrel ring; </l>
               <l>let's home, and sleep; for such great overthrows, </l>
               <l>a candle burns too bright a sacrifice, </l>
               <l>a glow-worms tail too full a flame. O Nennius, </l>
               <l>thou hadst a noble uncle knew a Romane, </l>
               <l>and how to speak him, how to give him weight</l>
               <l>in both his fortunes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000461">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> by---I think</l>
               <l>ye doat upon these Romanes,  Caratach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000471">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> witnesse these wounds, I do; they were fairly given.</l>
               <l>I love an enemy:I was born a souldier; </l>
               <l>and he that in the head on's troop defies me, </l>
               <l>bending my manly body with his sword, </l>
               <l>I make a mistris. Yellow-tressed hymen</l>
               <l>ne'er ty'd a longing virgin with more joy, </l>
               <l>then I am married to that man that wounds me:</l>
               <l>and are not all these Romane? Ten struck battels</l>
               <l>I suckt these honour'd scars from, and all Romane:</l>
               <l>ten yeers of bitter nights and heavie marches, </l>
               <l>when many a frozen storm sung thorow my curasse, </l>
               <l>and made it doubtful whether that or i</l>
               <l>were the more stubborn metal, have I wrought thorow, </l>
               <l>and all to try these Romanes. Ten times a night</l>
               <l>I have swom the rivers, when the stars of Rome</l>
               <l>shot at me as I floated, and the billows</l>
               <l>tumbled their watry ruines on my shoulders, </l>
               <l>charging my batter'd sides with troops of agues; </l>
               <l>and still to try these Romanes, whom I found</l>
               <l>(and if I lye, my wounds be henceforth backward, </l>
               <l>and be you witnesse, gods, and all my dangers)</l>
               <l>as ready, and as full of that I brought</l>
               <l>(which was not fear nor flight) as valiant, </l>
               <l>as vigilant,  as wise, to do and suffer, </l>
               <l>ever advanced as forward as the Britains, </l>
               <l>their sleeps as short, their hopes as high as ours, </l>
               <l>i,  and as subtil,  lady. 'Tis dishonour, </l>
               <l>and,  follow'd, will be impudence, Bonduca, </l>
               <l>and grow to no belief, to taint these Romanes.</l>
               <l>Have not I seen the Britains-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000565">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> what?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000572">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> dishearted, </l>
               <l>run,  run,  Bonduca, not the quick rack swifter:</l>
               <l>the virgin from the hated ravisher</l>
               <l>not half so fearful? Not a flight drawn home, </l>
               <l>a round stone from a sling, a lovers wish</l>
               <l>ere made that haste that they have. By-</l>
               <l>I have seen these Britains, that you magnifie, </l>
               <l>run as they would have out-run time, and roaring</l>
               <l>basely for mercy, roaring: the light shadows:</l>
               <l>that in a thought scur ore the fields of corn, </l>
               <l>halted on crutches to 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000609">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> o ye powers, </l>
               <l>what scandals do I suffer?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000619">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> yes, Bonduca, </l>
               <l>I have seen: thee run too, and thee, Nennius; </l>
               <l>yea,  run apace, both; then when Penyus</l>
               <l>the Romane girl cut thorow your armed carts, </l>
               <l>and drive 'em headlong on ye down the hill; </l>
               <l>then when he hunted ye, like Britain-foxes, </l>
               <l>more by the sent then sight: then did I see</l>
               <l>these valiant and approved men of Britain, </l>
               <l>like boading owls, creep into tods of ivie, </l>
               <l>and hoot their fears to one another nightly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000653">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> and what did you then,  Caratach?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000660">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I fled too, </l>
               <l>but not so fast; your jewel had been lost then, </l>
               <l>young Hengo there; he trasht me, Nennius:</l>
               <l>for when your fears out-run him, then stept i, </l>
               <l>and in the head of all the Romane fury</l>
               <l>took him, and with my tough belt to my back</l>
               <l>I buckled him; behinde him, my sure sheild; </l>
               <l>and then I follow'd. If I say I fought</l>
               <l>five times in bringing off this bud of Britain, </l>
               <l>I lye not, Nennius. Neither had ye heard</l>
               <l>me speake this, or ever seen the childe more, </l>
               <l>but that the son of vertue, Penyus, </l>
               <l>seeing me steer thorow all these storms of danger, </l>
               <l>my helm still in my hand, my sword my prow, </l>
               <l>turn'd to my fo my face, he cri'd out nobly, </l>
               <l>go,  Britain, bear thy lions whelp off safely; </l>
               <l>thy manly sword has ransom'd thee:grow strong, </l>
               <l>and let me meet thee once again in arms; </l>
               <l>then if thou stand'st, thou art mine. I took his offer, </l>
               <l>and here I am to honour him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000724">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> o cousin, </l>
               <l>from what a flight of honour hast thou checkt me?</l>
               <l>What wouldst thou make me,  Caratach?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000737">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> see, lady, </l>
               <l>the noble use of others in our losses; </l>
               <l>does this afflict ye? Had the Romanes cri'd this, </l>
               <l>and as we have done theirs, sung out these fortunes, </l>
               <l>rail'd on our base condition, hooted at us, </l>
               <l>made marks as far as the earth was ours,  to shew us, </l>
               <l>nothing but sea could stop our flights;  despis'd us; </l>
               <l>and held it equal whether banquetting</l>
               <l>or beating of the Britains were more businesse, </l>
               <l>it would have gall'd ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000771">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> let me think we conquer'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000778">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> do; but so think,  as we may be conquer'd:</l>
               <l>and where we have found vertue, though in those</l>
               <l>that came to make us slaves, let's cherish it.</l>
               <l>There's not a blowe we gave since julius landed, </l>
               <l>that was of strength and worth, but like records</l>
               <l>they file to after-ages. Our registers, </l>
               <l>the Romanes, are for noble deeds of honour; </l>
               <l>and shall we burn their mentions with upbraidings?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000806">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> no more, I see my self:thou hast made me, cousin, </l>
               <l>more then my fortunes durst; for they abus'd me, </l>
               <l>and wound me up so high, I swell'd with glory:</l>
               <l>thy temperance has cur'd that tympany, </l>
               <l>and given me health again, nay, more discretion.</l>
               <l>Shall we have peace?for now I love these Romanes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000828">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thy love and hate are both unwise ones, lady.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000835">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> your reason?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000842">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> is not peace the end of arms?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000849">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> not where the cause implies a general conquest:</l>
               <l>had we a difference with some pettie isle, </l>
               <l>or with our neighbours (lady)for our land marks, </l>
               <l>the taking in of some rebellious lord, </l>
               <l>or making a head against commotions, </l>
               <l>after a day of blood, peace might be argued:</l>
               <l>but where we grapple for the ground we live on, </l>
               <l>the libertie we hold as dear as life, </l>
               <l>the gods we worship, and next those, our honours, </l>
               <l>and with those swords that know no end of battel:</l>
               <l>those men beside themselves allow no neighbour; </l>
               <l>those mindes that where the day is claim inheritance, </l>
               <l>and where the sun makes ripe the fruits, their harvest, </l>
               <l>and where they march, but measure out more ground</l>
               <l>to adde to Rome, and here i'th'bowels on us; </l>
               <l>it must not be;  no,  as they are our foes, </l>
               <l>and those that must be so until we tire'em, </l>
               <l>let's use the peace of honour, that's fair dealing, </l>
               <l>but in our ends, our swords. That hardy Romane</l>
               <l>that hopes to graft himself into my stock, </l>
               <l>must first begin his kinred under ground, </l>
               <l>and be alli'd in ashes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000919">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> Caratach, </l>
               <l>as thou hast nobly spoken, shall be done; </l>
               <l>and Hengo to thy charge I here deliver:</l>
               <l>the Romanes shall have worthy wars.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000935">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> they shall.</l>
               <l>And,  little sir, when your young bones grow stiffer, </l>
               <l>and when I see ye able in a morning</l>
               <l>to beat a dozen boys, and then to breakfast, </l>
               <l>I'll tye ye to a sword.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000954">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> and what then, uncle?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000961">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> then ye must kill, sir, the next valiant Romane</l>
               <l>that calls ye knave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000971">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> and must I kill but one?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000978">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> an hundred, boy, I hope.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000985">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> I hope five hundred.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="5000000992">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> that's a noble boy. Come, worthy lady, </l>
               <l>let's to our several charges, and henceforth</l>
               <l>allow an enemy both weight and worth.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000001010">
               <head> Scaena Secunda</head>
            <stage>Enter Junius and Petillius, two Romane captains.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001017">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> what ailst thou, man? Dost thou want meat?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001024">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> no.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001031">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> clothes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001038">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> neither. For heavens love, leave me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001045">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> drink?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001052">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> ye tire me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001059">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> come, 't is drink; I know't is drink.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001066">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> 'tis no drink.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001073">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I say 't is drink:for what affliction</l>
               <l>can light so heavie on a souldier, </l>
               <l>to dry him up as thou art, but no drink?</l>
               <l>Thou shalt have drink.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001089">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> prethee,  Petillius-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001096">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> and by mine honour, much drink, valiant drink:</l>
               <l>never tell me, thou shalt have drink. I see, </l>
               <l>like a true friend, into thy wants: 'tis drink; </l>
               <l>and when I leave thee to a desolation, </l>
               <l>especially of that dry nature, hang me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001115">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> why do you do this to me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001122">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> for I see, </l>
               <l>although your modestie would fain conceal it, </l>
               <l>which sits as sweetly on a souldier, </l>
               <l>as an old side-saddle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001138">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> what do you see?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001145">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I see as far as day, that thou want'st drink.</l>
               <l>Did I not finde thee gaping like an oyster</l>
               <l>for a new tide? Thy very thoughts lie bare</l>
               <l>like a lowe ebbe? Thy soul that rid in sack, </l>
               <l>lies moor'd for want of liquor? Do but see</l>
               <l>into thy self; for by-I do:</l>
               <l>for all thy body's chapt, and crackt like timber</l>
               <l>for want of moisture:what thou wantst there, Junius, </l>
               <l>and if it be not drink.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001176">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> you have too much on't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001183">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> it may be a whore too; say it be:come, meecher, </l>
               <l>thou shalt have both:a pretty valiant fellow, </l>
               <l>die for a little lap and lechery?</l>
               <l>No, it shall ne'er be said in our countrey, </l>
               <l>thou dy'dst o'th'chin-cough. Heare, thou noble Romane, </l>
               <l>the son of her that loves a souldier, </l>
               <l>hear what I promised for thee; thus I said, </l>
               <l>lady, I take thy son to my companion, </l>
               <l>lady,  I love thy son, thy son loves war, </l>
               <l>the war loves danger, danger drink,  drink discipline, </l>
               <l>which is society and lechery; </l>
               <l>these two beget commanders:fear not, lady, </l>
               <l>thy son shall lead.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001226">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> 'tis a strange thing, Petillius, </l>
               <l>that so ridiculous and loose a mirth</l>
               <l>can master your affections.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001239">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> any mirth, </l>
               <l>and any way,  of any subject, Junius, </l>
               <l>is better then unmanly mustinesse:</l>
               <l>what harm's in drink, in a good wholesom wench?</l>
               <l>I do beseech ye, sir, what errour? Yet</l>
               <l>it cannot out of my head handsomly, </l>
               <l>but thou wouldst fain be drunk: come, no more fooling; </l>
               <l>the general has new wine, new come over.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001267">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> he must have new acquaintance for it too, </l>
               <l>for I will none, I thank ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001277">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> none, I thank ye?</l>
               <l>A short and touchie answer. None I thank ye:</l>
               <l>ye do not scorn it, do ye?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001290">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> gods defend sir; </l>
               <l>I owe him still more honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001300">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> none, I thank ye:</l>
               <l>no company, no drink, no wench, I thank ye.</l>
               <l>Ye shall be worse intreated, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001313">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> Petillius, </l>
               <l>as thou art honest, leave me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001323">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> none, I thank ye; </l>
               <l>a modest and a decent resolution, </l>
               <l>and well put on. Yes, I will leave ye,  Junius, </l>
               <l>and leave ye to the boys, that very shortly</l>
               <l>shall all salute ye, by your new sirname</l>
               <l>of Junius none I thanke ye. I would starve now, </l>
               <l>hang,  drown, despaire, deserve the forks, lie open</l>
               <l>to all the dangerous passes of a wench, </l>
               <l>bound to believe her tears, and wed her aches, </l>
               <l>ere I would own thy follies. I have found ye</l>
               <l>your lays, and out-leaps Junius, haunts, and lodges:</l>
               <l>I have view'd ye, and I have found ye by my skill</l>
               <l>to be a fool o'th'first head,  Junius, </l>
               <l>and I will hunt ye: ye are in love, I know it:</l>
               <l>ye are an asse, and all the camp shall know</l>
               <l>a peevish idle boy:your dame shall know it:</l>
               <l>a wronger of my care; your self shall know it.<stage>Enter corporal Judas, and four souldiers.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001381">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> a bean? A princely diet, a full banquet, </l>
               <l>to what we compasse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001391">
               <speaker>1 sould</speaker>
               <l> fight like hogs for acorns?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001398">
               <speaker>2 sould</speaker>
               <l> venture our lives for pig-nuts?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001405">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> what ail these rascals?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001412">
               <speaker>3 sould</speaker>
               <l> if this hold, we are starv'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001419">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> for my part, friends, </l>
               <l>which is but twenty beans a day, a hard world</l>
               <l>for officers, and men of action; </l>
               <l>and those so clipt by master mouse, and rotten:</l>
               <l>for understand 'em french beans, where the fruits</l>
               <l>are ripen'd like the people, in old tubs.</l>
               <l>For mine own part,  I say,  I am starv'd already, </l>
               <l>not worth another bean, consum'd to nothing, </l>
               <l>nothing but flesh and bones left, miserable:</l>
               <l>now if this mustie provender can prick me</l>
               <l>to honourable matters of atchievement,  gentlemen, </l>
               <l>why there's the point.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001459">
               <speaker>4 sould</speaker>
               <l> I'll fight no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001466">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> you'll hang then, </l>
               <l>a soveraign help for hunger. Ye eating rascals, </l>
               <l>whose gods are beef and brewis, whose brave angers</l>
               <l>do execution upon these, and chibbals:</l>
               <l>ye dogs heads i'th'porridge pot; you fight no more?</l>
               <l>Does Rome depend upon your resolution</l>
               <l>for eating mouldy pie-crust?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001491">
               <speaker>3 sould</speaker>
               <l> would we had it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001498">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> I may do service, captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001505">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> in a fish-market.</l>
               <l>You, corporal curry-comb, what will your fighting</l>
               <l>profit the common-wealth?do you hope to triumph, </l>
               <l>or dare your vamping valour, good man cobler, </l>
               <l>clap a new foal to th'kingdom? S'death, ye dog-whelps</l>
               <l>you,  fight, or not fight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001527">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001534">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> out, ye flesh-flyes, </l>
               <l>nothing but noyce and nastinesse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001544">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> give us meat, </l>
               <l>whereby we may do.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001554">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> whereby hangs your valor?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001561">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> good bits afford good blows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001568">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> a good position:</l>
               <l>how long is't since thou eat'st last? Wipe thy mouth, </l>
               <l>and then tell truth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001581">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> I have not eat to th'purpose-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001588">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> to th' purpose? What's that? Half a cow, and garlick?</l>
               <l>Ye rogues, my company eat turf, and talk not; </l>
               <l>timber they can digest, and fight upon't; </l>
               <l>old matts,  and mud with spoons, rare meats. Your shoes, slaves, </l>
               <l>dare ye cry out of hunger, and those extant?</l>
               <l>Suck your sword-hilts, ye slaves, if ye be valiant; </l>
               <l>honour will make 'em march-pain:to the purpose?</l>
               <l>A grievous penance. Dost thou see that gentleman, </l>
               <l>that melancholy monsieur?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001619">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> pray ye, Petillius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001626">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> he has not eat these three weeks.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001633">
               <speaker>2 sould</speaker>
               <l> 'has drunk the more then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001640">
               <speaker>3 sould</speaker>
               <l> and that's all one.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001647">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> nor drunk nor slept these two months.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001654">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> captain, we do beseech you as poor souldiers, </l>
               <l>men that have seen good days, whose mortal stomacks, </l>
               <l>may somtime feel afflictions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001667">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> this,  Petillius, </l>
               <l>is not so nobly done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001677">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> 'tis common profit; </l>
               <l>urge him to th'point, he'll finde you out a food</l>
               <l>that needs no teeth nor stomack; a strange formity</l>
               <l>will feed ye up as fat as hens i'th'foreheads, </l>
               <l>and make ye fight like fichocks,  to him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001696">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001703">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> do you long to have your throats cut?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001710">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> see what metal</l>
               <l>it makes in him:two meals more of this melancholy, </l>
               <l>and there lies Caratach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001723">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> we do beseech ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001730">
               <speaker>2 sould</speaker>
               <l> humbly beseech your valour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001737">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> am I onely</l>
               <l>become your sport,  Petillius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001747">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> but to render</l>
               <l>in way of general good, in preservation.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001757">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> out of my thoughts,  ye slaves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001764">
               <speaker>4 sould</speaker>
               <l> or rather pitie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001771">
               <speaker>3 sould</speaker>
               <l>your warlike remedy against the maw-worms.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001778">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> or notable receipt to live by nothing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001785">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> out with your table-books.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001792">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> is this true friendship?</l>
               <l>And must my killing griefs make others may-games?</l>
               <l>Stand from my swords point, slaves; your poor starv'd spirits</l>
               <l>can make me no oblations; else,  o love, </l>
               <l>thou proudly blind destruction, I would send thee</l>
               <l>whole hecatombs of hearts, to bleed my sorrows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001814">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> alas, he lives by love, sir,  <stage> exit Junius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001824">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> so he does, sir, </l>
               <l>and cannot you do so too? All my company</l>
               <l>are now in love, ne'er think of meat, nor talk</l>
               <l>of what provant is:aymees, and hearty hey-hoes, </l>
               <l>are sallets fit for souldiers. Live by meat, </l>
               <l>by larding up your bodies? 'T is lewd, and lazie, </l>
               <l>and shews ye meerly mortal,  dull,  and drives ye</l>
               <l>to fight like camels,  with baskets at your noses.</l>
               <l>Get ye in love;  ye can whore well enough, </l>
               <l>that all the world knows: fast ye into famine, </l>
               <l>yet ye can crawl like crabs to wenches, handsomly.</l>
               <l>Fall but in love now, as ye see example, </l>
               <l>and follow it but with all your thoughts,  probatum, </l>
               <l>there's so much charge sav'd,  and your hungers ended.</l>
               <l>Away, I hear the general: get ye in love all,  <stage>drum afar off</stage>
               </l>
               <l>up to the ears in love, that I may hear</l>
               <l>no more of these rude murmurings; and discreetly</l>
               <l>carry your stomacks, or I prophesie</l>
               <l>a pickel'd rope will choke ye. Jog,  and talk not.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Swetonius, Demetrius,  Decius,  drum,  colours.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001893">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> Demetrius, is the messenger dispatch'd</l>
               <l>to Penyus, to command him to bring up</l>
               <l>the volans regiment?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001906">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> he's there by this time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001913">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> and are the horse well view'd we brought from mona?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001920">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> the troops are full, and lusty.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001927">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> good Petillius, </l>
               <l>looke to those eating rogues, that bawl for victuals, </l>
               <l>and stop their throats a day or two:provision</l>
               <l>waits but the winde to reach us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001943">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> sir, already</l>
               <l>I have been tampring with their stomacks,  which I finde</l>
               <l>as deaf as adders to delays:your clemency</l>
               <l>hath made their murmurs,  mutinies,  nay,  rebellions:</l>
               <l>now,  and they want but mustard, they're in uproars:</l>
               <l>no oil but candy,  lucitanian figs, </l>
               <l>and wine from lestos, now can satisfie 'em:</l>
               <l>the british waters are grown dull and muddy, </l>
               <l>the fruit disgustful:orontes must be fought for, </l>
               <l>and apples from the happie isles:the truth is, </l>
               <l>they are more curious now in having nothing, </l>
               <l>then if the sea and land turn'd up their treasures:</l>
               <l>this lost the colonies, and gave Bonduca</l>
               <l>(with shame we must record it) time and strength</l>
               <l>to looke into our fortunes; great discretion</l>
               <l>to follow offered victory; and last, full pride</l>
               <l>to brave us to our teeth, and scorn our ruines.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000001998">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> nay, chide not,  good Petillius, I confesse</l>
               <l>my will to conquer mona, and long stay</l>
               <l>to execute that will, let in these losses:</l>
               <l>all shall be right again, and as a pine</l>
               <l>rent from oeta by a sweeping tempest, </l>
               <l>joynted again, and made a mast, defies</l>
               <l>those angry windes that split him:so will i, </l>
               <l>piec'd to my never-failing strength and fortune, </l>
               <l>steer thorow these swelling dangers, plow their prides up, </l>
               <l>and bear like thunder through their loudest tempests:</l>
               <l>they keep the field still.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002035">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> confident and full.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002042">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> in such a number, one would swear they grew, </l>
               <l>the hills are wooded with their partizans, </l>
               <l>and all the valleys over-grown with darts, </l>
               <l>as moors are with rank rushes:no ground left us</l>
               <l>to charge upon, no room to strike:say fortune</l>
               <l>and our endeavours bring us in to 'em, </l>
               <l>they are so infinite, so ever-springing, </l>
               <l>we shall be kill'd with killing; of desperate women, </l>
               <l>that neither fear, or shame ere found, the devill</l>
               <l>has rankt amongst 'em multitudes:say the men fail, </l>
               <l>they'll poison us with their petticoats:say they fail, </l>
               <l>they have priests enough to pray us into nothing, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002082">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> these are imaginations,  dreams of nothings, </l>
               <l>the man that doubts or fears.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002092">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> I am free of both.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002099">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> the self-same i.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002106">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> and I as free as any; </l>
               <l>as carelesse of my flesh, of that we call life, </l>
               <l>so I may lose it nobly; as indifferent</l>
               <l>as if it were my diet. Yet,  noble general, </l>
               <l>it was a wisedom learn'd from you; I learn'd it, </l>
               <l>and worthy of a souldiers care,  most worthy, </l>
               <l>to weigh with most deliberate circumstance</l>
               <l>the ends of accidents, above their offers; </l>
               <l>how to go on and get, to save a Romane, </l>
               <l>whose one life is more worth in way of doing, </l>
               <l>then millions of these painted wasps; how viewing</l>
               <l>to finde advantage out; how, found, to follow it</l>
               <l>with counsel and discretion, lest meer fortune</l>
               <l>should claim the victory.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002152">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> 'tis true, Petillius, </l>
               <l>and worthily remembred:the rule's certain, </l>
               <l>their uses no lesse excellent:but where time</l>
               <l>cuts off occasions,  danger,  time and all</l>
               <l>tend to a present peril, 'tis required</l>
               <l>our swords and manhoods be best counsellors, </l>
               <l>our expeditions,  presidents. To win, is nothing, </l>
               <l>where reason, time and counsel are our camp-masters:</l>
               <l>but there to bear the field, then to be conquerours, </l>
               <l>where pale destruction takes us, takes us beaten, </l>
               <l>in wants, and mutinies, our selves but handfuls, </l>
               <l>and to our selves our own fears,  needs a new way, </l>
               <l>a sudden and a desperate execution:</l>
               <l>here,  how to save,  is losse;  to be wise,  dangerous; </l>
               <l>onely a present well-united strength, </l>
               <l>and mindes made up for all attempts, dispatch it:</l>
               <l>disputing and delay here,  cools the courage; </l>
               <l>necessity gives time for doubts; things infinite, </l>
               <l>according to the spirit they are preach'd to, </l>
               <l>rewards like them; and names for after-ages, </l>
               <l>must steel the souldier; his own shame help to arm him; </l>
               <l>and having forc'd his spirit, ere he cools, </l>
               <l>fling him upon his enemies; sudden and swift, </l>
               <l>like tygers amongst foxes,  we must fight for't:</l>
               <l>fury must be our fortune; shame we have lost, </l>
               <l>spurs ever in our sides to prick us forward:</l>
               <l>there is no other wisedom nor discretion</l>
               <l>due to this day of ruine, but destruction; </l>
               <l>the souldiers order first, and then his anger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002243">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> no doubt they dare redeem all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002250">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> then no doubt</l>
               <l>the day must needs be ours. That the proud woman</l>
               <l>is infinite in number, better likes me, </l>
               <l>then if we dealt with squadrons:half her army</l>
               <l>shall choke themselves, their own swords dig their graves.</l>
               <l>I'll tell ye all my fears,  one single valour, </l>
               <l>the vertues of the valiant Caratach</l>
               <l>more doubts me then all Britain:he's a souldier</l>
               <l>so forg'd out, and so temper'd for great fortunes, </l>
               <l>so much man thrust into him, so old in dangers, </l>
               <l>so fortunate in all attempts, that his meer name</l>
               <l>fights in a thousand men, himself in millions, </l>
               <l>to make him Romane. But no more. Petillius, </l>
               <l>how stands your charge?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002296">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> ready for all employments, </l>
               <l>to be commanded too,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002306">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> 't is well govern'd; </l>
               <l>to morrow we'll draw out, and view the cohorts:</l>
               <l>i'th'mean time, all apply their offices.</l>
               <l>Where's Junius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002322">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> in's cabbin.</l>
               <l>Sick o'th'mumps,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002332">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> how?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002339">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> in love, indeed in love, most lamentably loving, </l>
               <l>to the tune of queen dido, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002349">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> alas poor gentleman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002356">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> 't will make him fight the nobler. With what lady?</l>
               <l>I'll be a spokesman for him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002366">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> you'll scant speed, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002373">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> who is't?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002380">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> the devils dam, Bonduca's daughter, </l>
               <l>her youngest, crackt i'th'ring.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002390">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> I am sorry for him:</l>
               <l>but sure his own discretion will reclaim him, </l>
               <l>he must deserve our anger else. Good captains, </l>
               <l>apply your selves in all the pleasing forms</l>
               <l>ye can, unto the souldiers; fire their spirits, </l>
               <l>and set 'em fit to run this action; </l>
               <l>mine owne provision shall be shar'd amongst 'em.</l>
               <l>Till more come in: tell 'em,  if now they conquer, </l>
               <l>the fat of all the kingdom lies before 'em, </l>
               <l>their shames forgot, their honours infinite, </l>
               <l>and want for ever banisht. Two days hence, </l>
               <l>our fortunes, and our swords, and gods be for us.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000002435">
               <head> Actus Secundus. Scaena Prima.</head>
            <stage>Enter Penyus,  Regulus,  Macer,  Drusius.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002442">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> I must come?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002449">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> so the general commands,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002456">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> I must bring up my regiment?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002463">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> believe, sir, </l>
               <l>I bring no lye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002473">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> but did he say,  I must come?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002480">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> so delivered.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002487">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> how long is't, Regulus, since I commanded</l>
               <l>in Britain here?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002497">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> about five yeers,  great Penyus.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002504">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> the general some five months. Are all my actions</l>
               <l>so poor, and lost, my services so barren, </l>
               <l>that i'm remembred in no nobler language</l>
               <l>but must come up?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002520">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> I do beseech ye, sir, </l>
               <l>weigh but the times estate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002530">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> yes, good lievtenant, </l>
               <l>I do, and his that sways it. Must come up?</l>
               <l>Am I turn'd bare centurion?must, and shall, </l>
               <l>fit embasses to court my honour?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002546">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> sir-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002553">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> set me to lead a handful of my men</l>
               <l>against an hundred thousand barbarous slaves</l>
               <l>that have marcht name by name with Romes best doers?</l>
               <l>Serve 'em up some other meat; I'll bring no food</l>
               <l>to stop the jaws of all those hungry wolfs.</l>
               <l>My regiment's mine own. I must, my language.<stage>Enter Curius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002578">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> Penyus, where lies the host?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002585">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> where fate may finde 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002592">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> are they ingirt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002599">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> the battel's lost.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002606">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> so soon?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002613">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> no; but 't is lost, because it must be won:</l>
               <l>the Britains must be victors. Who ere saw</l>
               <l>a troop of bloody vultures hovering</l>
               <l>about a few corrupted carcases, </l>
               <l>let him behold the silly Romane host, </l>
               <l>girded with millions of fierce Britain swains, </l>
               <l>with deaths as many as they have had hopes; </l>
               <l>and then go thither, he that loves his shame; </l>
               <l>I scorn my life, yet dare not lose my name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002644">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> do not you hold I a most famous end, </l>
               <l>when both our names and lives are sacrific'd</l>
               <l>for Romes encrease?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002657">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> yes, Curius; but mark this too; </l>
               <l>what glory is there, or what lasting fame</l>
               <l>can be to Rome, or us? What full example, </l>
               <l>when one is smother'd with a multitude, </l>
               <l>and crowded in amongst a namelesse presse?</l>
               <l>Honour got out of flint, and on their heads</l>
               <l>whose vertues, like the sun, exhal'd all valours, </l>
               <l>must not be left in mists and fogs of people, </l>
               <l>notelesse, and out of name, but rude and naked:</l>
               <l>nor can Rome task us with impossibilities, </l>
               <l>or bid us fight against a flood:we serve her, </l>
               <l>that she may proudly say she has good souldiers, </l>
               <l>nor slaves to choke all hazards. Who but fools, </l>
               <l>that make no difference betwixt certain dying, </l>
               <l>and dying well, would fling their fames and fortunes</l>
               <l>into this Britain-gulf, this quicksand-ruine, </l>
               <l>that sinking, swallows us? What noble hand</l>
               <l>can finde a subject fit for blood there? Or what sword</l>
               <l>room for his execution? What air to cool us, </l>
               <l>but poison'd with their blasting breaths and curses, </l>
               <l>where we lie buried quick above the ground, </l>
               <l>and are with labouring sweat, and breathlesse pain, </l>
               <l>kill'd like to slaves, and cannot kill again?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002730">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> Penyus,  mark ancient wars, and know that then</l>
               <l>captains weigh'd an hundred thousand men.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002740">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> Drusius,  mark ancient wisdom, and you'll finde then</l>
               <l>he gave the overthrow that sav'd his men.</l>
               <l>I must not go.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002753">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> the souldiers are desirous, </l>
               <l>their eagles all drawn out, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002763">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> who drew up Regulus?</l>
               <l>Ha? Speak: did you?whose bold will durst attempt this?</l>
               <l>Drawn out? Why, who commands, sir?on whose warrant</l>
               <l>durst they advance?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002779">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> I keep mine own obedience.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002786">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> 't is like the general cause, their love of honour, </l>
               <l>relieving of their wants.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002796">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> without my knowledge?</l>
               <l>Am I no more? My place but at their pleasures?</l>
               <l>Come,  who did this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002809">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> by-sir, I am ignorant.<stage> drum softly within: then enter souldiers with drum and colours.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002819">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> what, am I grown a shadow?heark, they march.</l>
               <l>I will know, and will be my self. Stand, disobedience:</l>
               <l>he that advances one foot higher,  dies for't.</l>
               <l>Run thorow the regiment upon your duties, </l>
               <l>and charge 'em on command:beat back again, </l>
               <l>by-I'll tith'em all else.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002841">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> we'll do our best.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.Drusius and Regulus.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002854">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> back; cease your bawling drums there, </l>
               <l>I'll beat the tubs about your brains else. Back:</l>
               <l>do I speak with lesse fear then thunder to ye?</l>
               <l>Must I stand to beseech ye? Home, home:ha?</l>
               <l>Do ye stare upon me?are those mindes I moulded, </l>
               <l>those honest valiant tempers I was proud</l>
               <l>to be a fellow to, those great discretions</l>
               <l>made your names fear'd and honour'd, turn'd to wildfires?</l>
               <l>O gods, to disobedience? Command, farewel; </l>
               <l>and be ye witnesse with me, all things sacred, </l>
               <l>I have no share in these mens shames. March, souldiers</l>
               <l>and seek your own sad ruines; your old Penyus</l>
               <l>dares not behold your murders.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002897">
               <speaker>sould</speaker>
               <l> captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002904">
               <speaker>2 sould</speaker>
               <l> captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002911">
               <speaker>3 sould</speaker>
               <l> dear honour'd captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002918">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> too too dear lov'd souldiers, </l>
               <l>which made ye weary of me:and heaven yet knows, </l>
               <l>though in your mutinies, I dare not hate you; </l>
               <l>take your own wills; 't is fit your long experience</l>
               <l>should now know how to rule your selves:I wrong ye, </l>
               <l>in wishing ye to save your lives and credits, </l>
               <l>to keep your necks whole from the ax hangs ore ye:</l>
               <l>alas, I much dishonour'd ye: go, seek the Britains, </l>
               <l>and say ye come to glut their sacrifices; </l>
               <l>but do not say I sent ye. What ye have been, </l>
               <l>how excellent in all parts, good, and govern'd, </l>
               <l>is onely left of my command, for story; </l>
               <l>what now ye are, for pitie. Fare ye well.<stage>Enter Drusius and Regulus.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002964">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> oh turn again, great Penyus; see the souldier</l>
               <l>in all points apt for duty.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002974">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> see his sorrow</l>
               <l>for his disobedience, which he says was haste, </l>
               <l>and haste (he thought) to please you with. See,  captain, </l>
               <l>the toughnesse of his courage turn'd to water; </l>
               <l>see how his manly heart melts.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000002993">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> go, beat homeward, </l>
               <l>there learn to eat your little with obedience, </l>
               <l>and henceforth strive to do as I direct ye.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt. souldiers.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003012">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> my answer, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003019">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> tell the great general, </l>
               <l>my companies are no fagots to fill breaches; </l>
               <l>my selfe no man that must, or shall, can carry:</l>
               <l>bid him be wise; and where he is, he's safe then; </l>
               <l>and when he findes out possibilities, </l>
               <l>he may command me. Commend me to the captains.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003041">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> all this I shall deliver.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003048">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> farewel, Macer. <stage> Exit Penyus.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003058">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> pray gods this breed no mischief.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003065">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> it must needs, </l>
               <l>if stout Swetonius win; for then his anger, </l>
               <l>besides the souldiers losse of due, and honour, </l>
               <l>will break together on him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003081">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> he's a brave fellow; </l>
               <l>and but a little hide his haughtinesse, </l>
               <l>(which is but sometimes neither, on some causes)</l>
               <l>he shews the worthiest Romane this day living.</l>
               <l>You may, good Curius, to the general</l>
               <l>make all things seem the best.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003103">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> I shall endeavour:</l>
               <l>pray for our fortunes, gentlemen. If we fall, </l>
               <l>this one farewel serves for a funeral.</l>
               <l>The gods make sharp our swords, and steel our hearts; </l>
               <l>we dare, alas, but cannot fight our parts.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000003130">
               <head> Scaena Secunda</head>
            <stage>Enter Junius,  Petillius and a herald.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003137">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> let him go on:stay, now he talks.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003144">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> why?</l>
               <l>Why should I love mine enemie? What is beauty?</l>
               <l>Of what strange violence, that like the plague, </l>
               <l>it works upon our spirits? Blind they faign him, </l>
               <l>I am sure, I find it so.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003163">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> a dog shall lead ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003170">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> his fond affections blinder.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003177">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> hold ye there still.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003184">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> it takes away my sleep, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003191">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> alas, poor chicken.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003198">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> my company, content; almost my fashion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003205">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> yes, and your weight too, if you follow it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003212">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> 'tis sure the plague, for no man dare come neer me</l>
               <l>without an antidote:'tis far worse; hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003222">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> thou art damn'd without redemption then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003229">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> the way to't</l>
               <l>strew'd with fair western smiles, and april blushes, </l>
               <l>led by the brightest constellations; eyes, </l>
               <l>and sweet proportions,  envying heaven:but from thence</l>
               <l>no way to guide, no path,  no wisdome brings us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003248">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> yes, a smart water,  Junius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003255">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> do I fool?</l>
               <l>Know all this, and fool still? Do I know further, </l>
               <l>that when we have enjoy'd our ends, we lose 'em, </l>
               <l>and all our appetites are but as dreams</l>
               <l>wee laugh at in our ages.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003274">
               <speaker>petil</speaker>
               <l> sweet philosopher</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003281">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> do I know on still and yet know nothing? Mercie gods, </l>
               <l>why am I thus ridiculous?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003291">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> motley on thee, </l>
               <l>thou art an arrant asse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003301">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> can red and white, </l>
               <l>an eye, a nose,  a cheek, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003311">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> but one cheek,  Junius?</l>
               <l>An half-fac'd mistris?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003321">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> with a little trim, </l>
               <l>that wanton fools call fashion, thus abuse mee?</l>
               <l>Take me beyond my reason?why should not i</l>
               <l>doat on my horse well trapt, my sword well hatch'd?</l>
               <l>They are as handsom things,  to mee more usefull, </l>
               <l>and possible to rule too. Did I but love, </l>
               <l>yet 'twere excusable, my youth would bear it; </l>
               <l>but to love there,  and that no time can give me, </l>
               <l>mine honour dare not ask: shee has been ravish'd</l>
               <l>my nature, must not know; she hates our nation.</l>
               <l>Thus to dispose my spirit</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003358">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> stay a little, </l>
               <l>he will declame again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003368">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I will not love; I am a man, have reason, </l>
               <l>and I will use it:I'll no more tormenting, </l>
               <l>nor whining for a wench, there are a thousand, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003381">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> hold thee there boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003388">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> a thousand will intreat me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003395">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> ten thousand, Junius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003402">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I am young and lustie, </l>
               <l>and to my fashion valiant; can please nightly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003412">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I'll swear thy back's probatum, for I have known thee</l>
               <l>leap at sixteen like a strong stallion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003422">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I will be man again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003429">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> now mark the working, </l>
               <l>the divell and the spirit tug for't: twenty pound</l>
               <l>upon the divels head.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003442">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I must be wretched.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003449">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I knew I had won.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003456">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> nor have I so much power</l>
               <l>to shun my fortune.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003466">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I will hunt thy fortune</l>
               <l>with all the shapes imagination breeds,  <stage> musick</stage>
               </l>
               <l>but I will fright thy divell:stay, he sings now.<stage> song, by Junius, and Petillius after him in mockage.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003484">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> must I be thus abus'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003491">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> yes mary must ye.</l>
               <l>Let's follow him close: oh, there he is, now read it.</l>
            </sp>
              <sp seasr:id="50000003501">
               <speaker>herald </speaker>
                <l>
                  <stage>reads</stage> it is the generals command, that all sick, </l>
               <l>persons old and unable, retire within the trenches;  hee that</l>
               <l>fears his libertie, to leave the field: fools, boyes, and lovers</l>
               <l>must not come neer the regiments,  for fear of their infections; </l>
               <l>especially those cowards they call lovers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003522">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> hah?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003529">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> read on.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003536">
               <speaker>herald</speaker>
               <l> if any common souldier love an enemie,  hee's</l>
               <l>whip'd and made a slave: if any captain; cast, with losse</l>
               <l>of honours,  flung out o'th' army, and made unable ever after</l>
               <l>to beare the name of a souldier.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003552">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> the-----consume ye all, rogues. <stage> exit Jun.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003562">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> let this work:</l>
               <l>h'as something now to chew upon:he's gone, </l>
               <l>come, shake no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003575">
               <speaker>her</speaker>
               <l> well, sir, you may command me, </l>
               <l>but not to doe the like again for europe:</l>
               <l>I would have given my life for a bent two-pence.</l>
               <l>If I ere read to lovers whilst I live again, </l>
               <l>or come within their confines-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003594">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> there's your payment, </l>
               <l>and keep this private.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003604">
               <speaker>her</speaker>
               <l> I am school'd for talking. <stage> Exit Herald.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Demetrius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003617">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> how now, Demetrius, are we drawn?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003624">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> 'tis doing:</l>
               <l>your company stands fair; but pray ye, where's Junius?</l>
               <l>Half his command are wanting, with some forty</l>
               <l>that Decius leads.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003640">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> hunting for victuals:</l>
               <l>upon my life free-booting rogues, their stomacks</l>
               <l>are like a widows lust, nere satisfied.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003653">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> I wonder how they dare stir, knowing the enemy</l>
               <l>master of all the countrey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003663">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> resolute hungers</l>
               <l>know neither fears, nor faiths, they tread on ladders, </l>
               <l>ropes,  gallowes, and overdoe all dangers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003676">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> they may be hang'd though.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003683">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> there's their joyfull supper, </l>
               <l>and no doubt they are at it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003693">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> but for heavens sake, </l>
               <l>how does young Junius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003703">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> drawing on, poor gentleman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003710">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> what, to his end?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003717">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> to th'end of all flesh:woman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003724">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> this love has made him a stout souldier.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003731">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> o, a great one, </l>
               <l>fit to command young goslings:but what news?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003741">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> I think the messenger's come back from Penyus</l>
               <l>by this time, let's go know.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003751">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> what will you say now</l>
               <l>if he deny to come, and take exceptions</l>
               <l>at some half syllable,  or found deliverd</l>
               <l>with an ill accent, or some stile left out?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003767">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> I cannot think he dare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003774">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> he dare speak treason, </l>
               <l>dare say, what no man dares beleeve, dares doe-</l>
               <l>but that's all one:I'll lay you my black armour</l>
               <l>to twenty crowns, he comes not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003790">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003797">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> you'll pay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003804">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> I will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003811">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> then keep thine old use Penyus, </l>
               <l>be stubborn and vain glorious, and I thank thee.</l>
               <l>Come let's go pray for six hours: most of us</l>
               <l>I fear,  will trouble heaven no more:two good blowes</l>
               <l>struck home at two commanders of the Britains, </l>
               <l>and my part's done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003833">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> I do not think of dying.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003840">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> 'tis possible we may live. But Demetrius, </l>
               <l>with what strange legs, and arms, and eyes,  and noses, </l>
               <l>let carpenters and copper-smiths consider.</l>
               <l>If I can keep my heart whole,  and my wind-pipe, </l>
               <l>that I may drink yet like a souldier-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003859">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> come, let's have better thoughts; mine's on</l>
               <l>your armour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003869">
               <speaker>petil</speaker>
               <l> mine's in your purse, sir:let's go try the wager.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000003884">
               <head> Scaena Tertia.</head>
            <stage>Enter Judas and his four companions (halters about
their necks) Bonduca,  her daughters,  Nennius following.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003891">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> come, hang'm presently.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003898">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> what made your rogueships</l>
               <l>harrying for victuals here? Are we your friends?</l>
               <l>Or doe you come for spies? Tell me directly, </l>
               <l>would you not willingly be hang'd now? Do not ye long for't?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003914">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> what say ye? Shall wee hang in this vain? Hang we must, </l>
               <l>and 'tis as good to dispatch it merrily, </l>
               <l>as pull an arse like dogs to't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003927">
               <speaker>1. Soul</speaker>
               <l> any way, </l>
               <l>so it be handsome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003937">
               <speaker>3. Soul</speaker>
               <l> I had as lief 'twere toothsom too:but all agree, </l>
               <l>and I'll not out boyes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003947">
               <speaker>4. Soul</speaker>
               <l> let's hang plesantly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003954">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> then plesantly be it: captain, the truth is, </l>
               <l>we had as lief hang with meat in our mouthes, </l>
               <l>as ask your pardon empty.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003967">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> these are brave hungers.</l>
               <l>What say you to a leg of beef now, sirha?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003977">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> bring me acquainted with it, and I'll tell ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003984">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> torment 'em wenches:I must back; then hang 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003991">
               <speaker>jud.</speaker>
               <l> we humbly thank your grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000003998">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> the rogues laugh at us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004005">
               <speaker>2.daugh</speaker>
               <l> sirha, what think you of a wench now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004012">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> a wench, lady?</l>
               <l>I do beseech your ladiship,  retire, </l>
               <l>I'll tell ye presently, ye see the time's short; </l>
               <l>one crash;  even to the setling of my conscience.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004028">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> why,  is't no more but up, boyes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004035">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> yes, ride too captain.</l>
               <l>Will you but see my feat?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004045">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> ye shall be set, sir, </l>
               <l>upon a jade shall shake ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004055">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> sheets,  good madam, </l>
               <l>will do it ten times better.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004065">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> whips,  good souldier, </l>
               <l>which ye shall taste before ye hang,  to mortifie ye; </l>
               <l>'tis pitie ye should die thus desperate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004078">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> these are the merry Romans,  the brave mad-caps.</l>
               <l>'Tis ten to one wee'll cool your resolutions.</l>
               <l>Bring out the whips.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004091">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> would your good ladyships</l>
               <l>would exercise 'em too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004101">
               <speaker>4. Soul</speaker>
               <l> surely ladies, </l>
               <l>we'ld shew you a strange patience.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004111">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> hang 'em rascals, </l>
               <l>they'l talk thus on the wheel. <stage>Enter Caratach.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004124">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> now what's the matter?</l>
               <l>What are these fellows? Whats the crime committed, </l>
               <l>that they wear necklaces?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004137">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> they are Roman rogues, </l>
               <l>taken a forraging.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004147">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> is that all,  Nennius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004154">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> would I were fairly hang'd; this is the divell, </l>
               <l>the kill-cow Caratach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004164">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> and you would hang 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004171">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> are they not enemies?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004178">
               <speaker>1. Soul</speaker>
               <l> my breech makes buttons.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004185">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> are they not our tormentors?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004192">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> tormentors? Flea-traps.</l>
               <l>Pluck off your halters,  fellows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004202">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> take heed,  Caratach, </l>
               <l>taint not your wisdome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004212">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> wisdome, Nennius?</l>
               <l>Why,  who shall fight against us, make our honours, </l>
               <l>and give a glorious day into our hands, </l>
               <l>if we dispatch our foes thus? What's their offence?</l>
               <l>Stealing a loafe or two to keep out hunger, </l>
               <l>a piece of greazie bacon, or a pudding?</l>
               <l>Do these deserve the gallows? They are hungry, </l>
               <l>poor hungry knaves, no meat at home left, starv'd:</l>
               <l>art thou not hungry?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004243">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> monstrous hungry.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004250">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> he looks like hungers self:get 'em some victuals, </l>
               <l>and wine to cheer their hearts,  quick: hang up poor pilchers?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004260">
               <speaker>2. Soul</speaker>
               <l> this is the bravest captain-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004267">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> Caratach, </l>
               <l>I'll leave you to your will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004277">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I'll answer all, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004284">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> let's up, and view his entertainment of 'em.</l>
               <l>I am glad they are shifted any way, their tongues else</l>
               <l>would still have murdred us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004297">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> let's up, and see it.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Hengo.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004310">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> sit down poor knaves:why, where's this wine</l>
               <l>and victuals?</l>
               <l>Who waites there?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004323">
               <speaker>suit</speaker>
               <stage> within</stage>
               <l> sir,  'tis coming.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004333">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> who are these uncle?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004340">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thy are Romans,  boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004347">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> are these they</l>
               <l>that vex mine aunt so? Can these fight? They look</l>
               <l>like emptie scabbards,  all,  no mettle in 'em, </l>
               <l>like men of clouts, set to keep crows from orchards; </l>
               <l>why, I dare fight with these.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004366">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> that's my good chicken. And how do ye?</l>
               <l>How do you feel your stomacks?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004376">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> wondrous apt, sir, </l>
               <l>as shall appear when time calls.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004386">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> that's wel, down with't, </l>
               <l>a little grace will serve your turns:eat softly, </l>
               <l>you'll choak ye knaves else: give 'em wine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004399">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> not yet, sir, </l>
               <l>we're even a little busie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004409">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> can that fellow</l>
               <l>do any thing but eat? Thou fellow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004419">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> away boy, </l>
               <l>away, this is no boyes play.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004429">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> by---,  uncle, </l>
               <l>is his valour lie in's teeth, he's the most valiant.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004439">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I am glad to hear ye talk, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004446">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> good uncle tell me, </l>
               <l>what's the price of a couple of cramm'd Romans?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004456">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> some twenty Britains boy; these are good soldiers, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004463">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> do not the cowards eat hard too?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004470">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> no more, boy.</l>
               <l>Come,  I'll sit with you too;  sit down by me, boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004480">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> pray bring your dish then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004487">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> hearty knaves:more meat there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004494">
               <speaker>1. Soul</speaker>
               <l> that's a good hearing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004501">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> stay now and pledge me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004508">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> this little piece sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004515">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> by-----square eaters, </l>
               <l>more meat I say; upon my conscience</l>
               <l>the poor rogues have not eat this month:how terribly</l>
               <l>they charge upon their victuals:dare ye fight thus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004531">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> beleeve it sir, like devils, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004538">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> wel said famine, </l>
               <l>here's to thy general.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004548">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> most excellent captain, I wil now pledge thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004555">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> and to morrow night, say to him, </l>
               <l>his head is mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004565">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> I can assure ye captain, </l>
               <l>he wil not give it for this washing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004575">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> wel said. <stage> daughters above.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004585">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> here's a strange entertainment: how the</l>
               <l>theeves drink.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004595">
               <speaker>2. Daug</speaker>
               <l> danger is dry, they look'd for colder liquor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004602">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> fil 'em more wine, give 'em ful bowls; which of</l>
               <l>you all now</l>
               <l>in recompence of this good,  dare but give me</l>
               <l>a sound knock in the battell?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004618">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> delicate captain, </l>
               <l>to doe thee a sufficient recompence, </l>
               <l>I'll knock thy brains out.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004631">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> do it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004638">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> thou dar'st as well be damn'd: thou knock his</l>
               <l>brains out.</l>
               <l>Thou skin of man? Uncle, I will not hear this.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004651">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> tie up your whelp.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004658">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> thou kill my uncle?</l>
               <l>Would I had but a sword for thy sake, thou dry'd dog.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004668">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> what a mettle</l>
               <l>this little vermine caries.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004678">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> kill mine uncle?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004685">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> he shall not, child.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004692">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> he cannot:he's a rogue, </l>
               <l>an onely eating rogue: kill my sweet uncle?</l>
               <l>Oh that I were a man.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004705">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> by this wine, </l>
               <l>which I will drink to captain Junius, </l>
               <l>who loves the queens most excellent majesties little daughter</l>
               <l>most sweetly, and most fearfully, I will do it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004721">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> uncle, I'll kill him with a great pin.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004728">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> no more, boy.</l>
               <l>I'll pledge thy captain:to ye all, good fellows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004738">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> in love with me? That love shall cost your</l>
               <l>lives all:</l>
               <l>come sister,  and advise me; I have here</l>
               <l>a way to make an easie conquest of 'em, </l>
               <l>if fortune favour me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004757">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> let's see ye sweat</l>
               <l>to morrow, blood and spirit, boyes, this wine</l>
               <l>turn'd to sterne valour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004770">
               <speaker>1. Soul</speaker>
               <l> heark ye Judas, </l>
               <l>if he should hang us after all this.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004780">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> let him:</l>
               <l>I'll hang like a gentleman, and a Roman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004790">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> take away there, </l>
               <l>they have enough.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004800">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> captain, wee thank you heartily</l>
               <l>for your good cheer, and if we meet to morrow, </l>
               <l>one of us payes for't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004813">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> get 'em guides, their wine <stage>Enter 2d daughter and a servant</stage>
               </l>
               <l>has over master'd 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004825">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> that hungry fellow</l>
               <l>with the red beard there, give it him, and this, </l>
               <l>to see it well deliverd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004838">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> farewell,  knaves; </l>
               <l>speak nobly of us, keep your words to morrow, <stage>Enter a guide</stage>
               </l>
               <l>and doe something worthy your meat. Go,  guide 'em, </l>
               <l>and see 'em fairly onward.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004856">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> meaning me, sir?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004863">
               <speaker>serv</speaker>
               <l> the same.</l>
               <l>The youngest daughter to the queen intreats ye</l>
               <l>to give this privately to captain Junius, </l>
               <l>this for your pains.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004879">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> I rest her humble servant.</l>
               <l>Commend me to thy lady. Keep your files, boyes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004889">
               <speaker>serv</speaker>
               <l> I must instruct ye farther.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004896">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> keep your files there.</l>
               <l>Order,  sweet friends: faces about now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004906">
               <speaker>guide</speaker>
               <l> here sir, </l>
               <l>here lies your way.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004916">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> 'blesse the founders,  I say.</l>
               <l>Fairly,  good souldiers,  fairly march now: close, boyes.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000004934">
               <head> Scaena Quarta.</head>
            <stage>Enter Swetonius,  Petillius,  Demetrius,  Decius,  Macer.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004941">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> bid me be wise, and keep me where I am, </l>
               <l>and so be safe: not come, because commanded; </l>
               <l>was it not thus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004954">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> it was, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004961">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> what now think ye?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004968">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> must come, so hainous to him, so distastefull?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004975">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> give me my money.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004982">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> I confesse 'tis due sir, </l>
               <l>and presently I'll pay it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000004992">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> his obedience</l>
               <l>so blind at his yeers and experience, </l>
               <l>it cannot find where to be tendred?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005005">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> sir, </l>
               <l>the regiment was willing, and advanc'd too, </l>
               <l>the captains at all points steel'd up; their preparations</l>
               <l>full of resolve, and confidence; youth and fire, </l>
               <l>like the fair breaking of a glorious day, </l>
               <l>guilded their falanx:when the angrie Penyus</l>
               <l>stept like a stormy cloud 'twixt them and hopes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005030">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> and stopt their resolutions?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005037">
               <speaker>Ma</speaker>
               <l> true: his reason</l>
               <l>to them was ods, and ods so infinite, </l>
               <l>discretion durst not look upon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005050">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> well Penyus, </l>
               <l>I cannot think thee coward yet; and treacherous</l>
               <l>I dare not think:thou hast lopt a limb off from me, </l>
               <l>and let it be thy glory, thou wast stubborn, </l>
               <l>thy wisdome, that thou leftst thy generall naked:</l>
               <l>yet ere the sun set, I shall make thee see, </l>
               <l>all valour dwels not in thee; all command</l>
               <l>in one experience. Thou wilt too late repent this, </l>
               <l>and wish, I must come up, had been thy blessing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005081">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> let's force him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005088">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> no, by no means; he's a torrent</l>
               <l>we cannot easily stemme.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005098">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I think, a traitor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005105">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> no il words:let his own shame first revile him.</l>
               <l>That wine I have, see it (Demetrius)</l>
               <l>distributed amongst the souldiers, </l>
               <l>to make 'em high and lustie: when that's done, </l>
               <l>Petillius, give the word through, that the eagles</l>
               <l>may presently advance:no man discover, </l>
               <l>upon his life, the enemies full strength, </l>
               <l>but make it of no value:Decius, </l>
               <l>are your starv'd people yet come home?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005136">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> I hope so.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005143">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> keep 'em in more obedience:this is no time</l>
               <l>to chide, I could be angry else, and say more to ye:</l>
               <l>but come, let's order all: whose sword is sharpest, </l>
               <l>and valour equall to his sword this day, </l>
               <l>shall by my saint.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005162">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> we shall be holy all then.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Judas and his company.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005175">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> captain,  captain,  I have brought 'em off again; </l>
               <l>the drunkenest slaves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005185">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> ---confound your rogueships; </l>
               <l>I'll call the generall, and have ye hang'd all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005195">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> pray who will you command then?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005202">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> for you, sirha, </l>
               <l>that are the ring-leader to these devises, </l>
               <l>whose maw is never cramm'd, I'll have an engine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005215">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> a wench, sweet captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005222">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> sweet Judas, even the forks.</l>
               <l>Where ye shall have two lictors with two whips</l>
               <l>hammer your hide.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005235">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> captain,  good words, fair words, </l>
               <l>sweet words,  good captain; if you like not us, </l>
               <l>farewell, we have imployment.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005248">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> where hast thou been?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005255">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> there where you dare not be with all your valour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005262">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> where's that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005269">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> with the best good-fellow living.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005276">
               <speaker>1. Soul</speaker>
               <l> the king of all good-fellows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005283">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> who's that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005290">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> Caratach.</l>
               <l>Shake now, and say , wee have done something worthie, </l>
               <l>mark me;  with Caratach: by this---Caratach:</l>
               <l>do you asmuch now and you dare: sweet Caratach.</l>
               <l>Ye talk of a good fellow, of true drinking; </l>
               <l>wel,  go thy waies, old Caratach:besides the drink captain, </l>
               <l>the bravest running banquet of black puddings, </l>
               <l>peeces of glorious beef.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005318">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> how scapt ye hanging?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005325">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> hanging's a dogs death: we are gentlemen, </l>
               <l>and I say still, old Caratach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005335">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> belike then, </l>
               <l>you are turn'd rebels all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005345">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> we are Roman boyes all, </l>
               <l>and boyes of mettle:I must doe that captain, </l>
               <l>this day, this very day.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005358">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> away, ye rascal.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005365">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> fair words, I say again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005372">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> what must you doe, sir?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005379">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> I must do that my heart-strings yern to do:</l>
               <l>but my word's past.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005389">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> what is it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005396">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> why, kill Caratach.</l>
               <l>That's all he ask'd us for our entertainment.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005406">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> more then you'll pay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005413">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> would I had sold my self</l>
               <l>unto the skie, I had not promis'd it:</l>
               <l>for such another Caratach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005426">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> come fool, </l>
               <l>have ye done your country service?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005436">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> I have brought that</l>
               <l>to captain iunius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005446">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> how?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005453">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> I think will doe all:</l>
               <l>I cannot tell,  I think so.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005463">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> how? To iunius?</l>
               <l>I'le more enquire of this:you'll fight now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005473">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> promise:</l>
               <l>take heed of promise, captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005483">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> away, and rank then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005490">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> but heark ye captain, there is wine distributing, </l>
               <l>I would fain know what share I have.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005500">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> be gone.</l>
               <l>Ye have too much.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005510">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> captain, no wine, no fighting.</l>
               <l>There's one call'd Caratach, that has wine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005520">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> well sir, </l>
               <l>if you'll be rul'd now, and doe well.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005530">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> doe excellent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005537">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> ye shall have wine, or any thing; goe file; </l>
               <l>I'll see ye have your share:drag out your dormise, </l>
               <l>and stow 'em somwhere, where they may sleep handsomly, </l>
               <l>they'l hear a hunt's up shortly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005553">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> now I love thee:</l>
               <l>but no more forks nor whips.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005563">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> deserve 'em not then:</l>
               <l>up with your men, I'll meet ye presently; </l>
               <l>and get 'em sober quickly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005576">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> arm,  arm,  bullyes; </l>
               <l>all's right again and straight;  and which is more, </l>
               <l>more wine,  more wine: awake ye men of memphis, </l>
               <l>be sober and discreet, we have much to do boyes.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000005597">
               <head> Actus Tertius. Scaena Prima.</head>
            <stage>Enter a messenger.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005604">
               <speaker>mess</speaker>
               <l> prepare there for the sacrifice, the queen comes. <stage> musick</stage>
                  <stage> enter in solemnity, the druids singing, the second
daughter strewing flowers: then Bonduca,  Caratach,  Nennius,  and others.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005615">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> ye powerfull gods of Britain, hear our prayers; </l>
               <l>hear us you great revengers, and this day</l>
               <l>take pitie from our swords, doubt from our valours, </l>
               <l>double the sad remembrance of our wrongs</l>
               <l>in every brest; the vengeance due to those</l>
               <l>make infinite and endlesse:on our pikes</l>
               <l>this day pale terror sit, horrors and ruines</l>
               <l>upon our executions; claps of thunder</l>
               <l>hang on our armed carts, and 'fore our troops</l>
               <l>despair and death; shame beyond these attend 'em.</l>
               <l>Rise from the dust, ye relicks of the dead, </l>
               <l>whose noble deeds our holy druids sing, </l>
               <l>oh rise, ye valiant bones,  let not base earth</l>
               <l>oppresse your honours, whilest the pride of Rome</l>
               <l>treads on your stocks, and wipes out all your stories.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005664">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> thou great tiranes, whom our sacred priests, </l>
               <l>armed with dreadfull thunder, place on high</l>
               <l>above the rest of the immortall gods, </l>
               <l>send thy consuming fires and deadly bolts, </l>
               <l>and shoot 'em home; stick in each Roman heart</l>
               <l>a fear fit for confusion; blast their spirits, </l>
               <l>dwell in 'em to destruction; thorow their phalanx</l>
               <l>strike, as thou strik'st a proud tree; shake their bodies, </l>
               <l>make their strengths totter, and their toplesse fortunes</l>
               <l>unroot, and reel to ruine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005698">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> o thou god, </l>
               <l>thou feared god, if ever to thy justice</l>
               <l>insulting wrongs,  and ravishments of women, </l>
               <l>women deriv'd from thee,  their shames,  the suffrings</l>
               <l>of those that daily fill'd thy sacrifice</l>
               <l>with virgin incense, have accesse, now hear me, </l>
               <l>now snatch thy thunder up, now on these Romans, </l>
               <l>despisers of thy power, of us defacers, </l>
               <l>revenge thy self; take to thy killing anger, </l>
               <l>to make thy great work full, thy justice spoken, </l>
               <l>an utter rooting from this blessed isle</l>
               <l>of what Rome is or has been.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005738">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> give more incense, </l>
               <l>the gods are deafe and drowsie;  no happy flame</l>
               <l>rises to raise our thoughts: pour on.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005751">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> see heaven, </l>
               <l>and all you pow'rs that guide us, see, and shame</l>
               <l>we kneel so long for pitie over your altars; </l>
               <l>since 'tis no light oblation that you look for, </l>
               <l>no incense offring, will I hang mine eyes; </l>
               <l>and as I wear these stones with hourly weeping, </l>
               <l>so will I melt your pow'rs into compassion.</l>
               <l>This tear for prosutagus my brave father, </l>
               <l>ye gods, now think on Rome; this for my mother, </l>
               <l>and all her miseries; yet see, and save us:</l>
               <l>but now ye must be open ey'd. See,  heaven, </l>
               <l>o see thy showrs stoln from thee;  our dishonours,  <stage> a smoak from the altar</stage>
               </l>
               <l>o sister,  our dishonours: can ye be gods, </l>
               <l>and these sins smother'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005799">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> the fire takes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005806">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> it does so, </l>
               <l>but no flame rises,  cease your fearfull prayers, </l>
               <l>your whinings, and your tame petitions; </l>
               <l>the gods love courage arm'd with confidence, </l>
               <l>and prayers fit to pull them down:weak tears</l>
               <l>and troubled hearts, the dull twins of cold spirits, </l>
               <l>they sit and smile at. Hear how I salute 'em:</l>
               <l>divine audate, thou who hold'st the reins</l>
               <l>of furious battels, and disordred war, </l>
               <l>and proudly roll'st thy swarty chariot wheels</l>
               <l>over the heaps of wounds, and carcasses, </l>
               <l>sailing through seas of bloud;  thou sure-steel'd sternnesse, </l>
               <l>giue us this day good hearts,  good enemies, </l>
               <l>good blowes o'both sides,  wounds that fear or flight</l>
               <l>can claim no share in; steel us both with angers, </l>
               <l>and warlike executions fit thy viewing; </l>
               <l>let Rome put on her best strength, and thy Britain, </l>
               <l>thy little Britain, but as great in fortune, </l>
               <l>meet her as strong as shee, as proud,  as daring; </l>
               <l>and then look on, thou red ey'd god: who does best, </l>
               <l>reward with honour;  who despair makes flie, </l>
               <l>unarme for ever, and brand with infamie:</l>
               <l>grant this, divine audate,  't is but justice; </l>
               <l>and my first blow thus on thy holy altar <stage> a flame arises</stage>
               </l>
               <l>I sacrifise unto thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005887">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> it flames out.<stage> musick.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005897">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> now sing ye druides. <stage> song.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005907">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> 'tis out again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005914">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> h'as given us leave to fight yet;  we ask no more, </l>
               <l>the rest hangs in our resolutions:</l>
               <l>tempt him no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005927">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> I would know further cosen, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005934">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> his hidden meaning dwels in our endeavours; </l>
               <l>our valours are our best gods. Cheer the souldier, </l>
               <l>and let him eat.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005947">
               <speaker>mess</speaker>
               <l> he's at it, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005954">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> away then; </l>
               <l>when he has done, let's march. Come,  fear not lady, </l>
               <l>this day the Roman gains no more ground here, </l>
               <l>but what his body lies in.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005970">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> now I am confident.  <stage>Exeunt recorders.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000005982">
               <head> Scaena Secunda</head>
            <stage>Enter Junius,  Curius,  Decius.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005989">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> we dare not hazzard it:beside our lives, </l>
               <l>it forfeits all our understandings.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000005999">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> gentlemen, </l>
               <l>can ye forsake me in so just a service, </l>
               <l>a service for the common-wealth, for honour?</l>
               <l>Read but the letter; you may love too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006015">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> read it:</l>
               <l>if there be any safety in the circumstance, </l>
               <l>or likelihood 'tis love we will not faile ye.</l>
               <l>Read it good Curius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006031">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> willingly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006038">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> now mark it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006045">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <stage> reads</stage>
               <l> health to thy heart, my honourd Junius, </l>
               <l>and all thy love requited:I am thine, </l>
               <l>thine everlastingly, thy love has won me, </l>
               <l>and let it breed no doubt;  our new acquaintance</l>
               <l>compels this,  'tis the gods decree to blesse us.</l>
               <l>The times are dangerous to meet; yet fail not, </l>
               <l>by all the love thou bear'st me I conjure thee, </l>
               <l>without distrust of danger, to come to me, </l>
               <l>for I have purpos'd a delivery</l>
               <l>both of my self and fortune this blest day</l>
               <l>into thy hands, if thou thinkst good:to shew thee</l>
               <l>how infinite my love is, even my mother</l>
               <l>shall be thy prisoner, the day yours without hazzard; </l>
               <l>for I beheld your danger like a lover, </l>
               <l>a just affecter of thy faith: thy goodnesse, </l>
               <l>I know,  will use us nobly, and our marriage, </l>
               <l>if not redeem, yet lessen Romes ambition.</l>
               <l>I am weary of these miseries: use my mother, </l>
               <l>(if you intend to take her) with all honour, </l>
               <l>and let this disobedience to my parents</l>
               <l>be laid on love, not me. Bring with thee,  Junius, </l>
               <l>spirits resolv'd to fetch me off, the noblest, </l>
               <l>forty will serve the turn; just at the joyning</l>
               <l>of both the battels, we will be weakly guarded; </l>
               <l>and for a guide, within this hour shall reach thee</l>
               <l>a faithfull friend of mine:the gods, my Junius, </l>
               <l>keep thee, and me to serve thee:young bonvica.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006133">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> this letter carries much belief, and most objections</l>
               <l>answer'd,  we must have doubted.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006143">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> is that fellow</l>
               <l>come to ye for a guide yet?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006153">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006160">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> and examin'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006167">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> far more then that;  he has felt tortures, yet</l>
               <l>he vows he knows no more then this truth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006177">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> strange.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006184">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> if she mean what she writes,  as't may be probable, </l>
               <l>'twill be the happiest vantage we can lean to.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006194">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I'll pawn my soul she means truth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006201">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> think an hour more, </l>
               <l>then if your confidence grow stronger on ye, </l>
               <l>we'll set in with ye</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006214">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> nobly done; I thank ye; </l>
               <l>ye know the time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006224">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> we will be either ready</l>
               <l>to give ye present counsell, or joyne with ye. <stage>Enter Swetonius,  Petillius, and Demetrius,  Macer.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006236">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> no more as ye are gentlemen. The generall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006243">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> draw out a pace,  the enemy waits for us; </l>
               <l>are ye all ready?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006253">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> all our troops attend, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006260">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> I am glad to hear you say so,  Junius.</l>
               <l>I hope ye are dispossest.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006270">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I hope so too, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006277">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> continue so. And gentlemen, to you now; </l>
               <l>to bid you fight is needlesse, ye are Romans, </l>
               <l>the name will fight it self; to tell ye who</l>
               <l>you go to fight against, his power, and nature, </l>
               <l>but losse of time:ye know it, know it poor, </l>
               <l>and oft have made it so. To tell ye further, </l>
               <l>his bodie showes more dreadfull then it has done, </l>
               <l>to him that fears,  lesse possible to deal with, </l>
               <l>is but to stick more honour on your actions, </l>
               <l>load ye with vertuous names, and to your memories</l>
               <l>tie never dying time, and fortune constant.</l>
               <l>Go on in full assurance,  draw your swords</l>
               <l>as daring and as confident as justice; </l>
               <l>the gods of Rome fight for ye; loud fame calls ye, </l>
               <l>pitch'd on the toplesse perinine, and blows</l>
               <l>to all the under world:all nations, </l>
               <l>the seas, and unfrequented deserts, where the snow dwels, </l>
               <l>wakens the ruin'd monuments, and there</l>
               <l>where nothing but eternall death and sleep is, </l>
               <l>informs again the dead bones. With your vertues, </l>
               <l>go on,  I say,  valiant and wise, rule heaven, </l>
               <l>and all the great aspects attend 'em. Do but blow</l>
               <l>upon this enemy,  who, but that we want foes, </l>
               <l>cannot deserve that name;  and like a myst, </l>
               <l>a lazie fog, before your burning valours</l>
               <l>you'll finde him flie to nothing. This is all, </l>
               <l>we have swords, and are the sons of ancient Romans, </l>
               <l>heirs to their endlesse valours,  fight and conquer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006365">
               <speaker>de. Dem</speaker>
               <l> 'tis done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006372">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> that man that loves not this day, </l>
               <l>and hugs not in his arms the noble danger, </l>
               <l>may he die famelesse and forgot.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006385">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> sufficient, </l>
               <l>up to your troops, and let your drums beat thunder, </l>
               <l>march close, and sudden like a tempest:all executions <stage> march</stage>
               </l>
               <l>done without sparkling of the body:keep your phalanx</l>
               <l>sure lin'd, and piec'd together; your pikes forward, </l>
               <l>and so march like a moving fort: ere this day run, </l>
               <l>we shal have ground to add to Rome, wel won.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000006417">
               <head> Scaena Tertia.</head>
            <stage>Enter Caratach and Nennius.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006424">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> the Roman is advanc'd from yound'hils brow, </l>
               <l>we may behold him,  Caratach. <stage> a march</stage>
                  <stage> drums within at one place afar off.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006439">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> let's thither, </l>
               <l>I see the dust flie. Now I see the body, </l>
               <l>observe 'em ,  Nennius; by-----a handsome body, </l>
               <l>and of a few, strongly and wisely joynted:</l>
               <l>Swetonius is a souldier.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006458">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> as I take it, </l>
               <l>that's hee that gallops by the regiments, </l>
               <l>viewing their preparations.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006471">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> very likely, </l>
               <l>he shews no lesse then generall:see how bravely</l>
               <l>the body moves, and in the head how proudly</l>
               <l>the captains stick like plumes:hee comes apace on; </l>
               <l>good Nennius go, and bid my stout leutenant</l>
               <l>bring on the first square bodie to oppose 'em, </l>
               <l>and as he charges,  open to enclose 'em:</l>
               <l>the queen move next with hers,  and wheel about, </l>
               <l>to gain their backs, in which I'll lead the vantguard.</l>
               <l>We shall have bloody crowns this day, I see by't; </l>
               <l>haste thee good Nennius, I'll follow instantly.<stage> exit Nennius</stage>
               </l>
               <l>how close they march, as if they grew together? <stage> march</stage>
               </l>
               <l>no place but lin'd alike: sure from oppression; </l>
               <l>they will not change this figure: we must charge 'em, </l>
               <l>and charge 'em home at both ends,  van and rere, <stage> drums in another place afar off</stage>
               </l>
               <l>they never totter else. I hear our musick, </l>
               <l>and must attend it:hold good sword, but this day, </l>
               <l>and bite hard where I hound thee, and hereafter</l>
               <l>I'll make a relique of thee, for young souldiers</l>
               <l>to come like pilgrimes to, and kisse for conquests.<stage> exit</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000006545">
               <head> Scaena Quarta.</head>
            <stage>Enter Junius,  Curius,  and Decius.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006552">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> now is the time,  the fellow stayes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006559">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> what think yee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006566">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> I think 'tis true.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006573">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> alas, if 'twere a question, </l>
               <l>if any doubt or hazzard fell into't, </l>
               <l>do ye think mine own discretion so self-blinde, </l>
               <l>my care of you so naked, to run headlong?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006589">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> let's take Petillius with us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006596">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> by no means:</l>
               <l>hee's never wise but to himself, nor courteous, </l>
               <l>but where the end's his own:we are strong enough, </l>
               <l>if not too many. Behind yonder hill</l>
               <l>the fellow tels me she attends,  weak guarded, </l>
               <l>her mother and her sister.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006618">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> I would venture.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006625">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> wee shall not strike five blows for't: weigh the good, </l>
               <l>the generall good may come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006635">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> away, I'll with ye, </l>
               <l>but with what doubt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006645">
               <speaker>fun</speaker>
               <l> fear not, my soul for all.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Alarms,  drums and trumpets in severall places afar off,  as at a main battel.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000006658">
           
               <head> scaena quinta.</head>
            <stage>Enter Drusus and Penyus above.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006665">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> here ye may see 'em all, sir; from this hill</l>
               <l>the country shews off levell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006675">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> gods defend me, </l>
               <l>what multitudes they are, what infinites?</l>
               <l>The Roman power shews like a little star</l>
               <l>hedg'd with a double halloa. Now the knell rings, <stage> loud shouts</stage>
               </l>
               <l>heark how they shout to th'battell; how the air</l>
               <l>totters and reels, and rends apieces, Drusus, </l>
               <l>with the huge vollied clamours.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006702">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> now they charge.</l>
               <l>Oh gods, of all sides,  fearfully.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006712">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> little Rome, </l>
               <l>stand but this growing hydra one short hour, </l>
               <l>and thou hast out-done hercules.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006725">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> the dust hides 'em, </l>
               <l>we cannot see what follows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006735">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> they are gone, </l>
               <l>gone,  swallow'd,  Drusus; this eternall sun</l>
               <l>shall never see 'em march more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006748">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> o turn this way, </l>
               <l>and see a modell of the field, some forty, </l>
               <l>against four hundred.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006761">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> well fought, bravely follow'd; </l>
               <l>o nobly charg'd again,  charg'd home too: Drusus, </l>
               <l>they seem to carry it:now they charge all,  <stage> loud</stage>
               </l>
               <l>close,  close,  I say;  they follow it: ye gods, </l>
               <l>can there be more in men? More daring spirits?</l>
               <l>Stil they make good their fortunes. Now they are gone too, </l>
               <l>for ever gone: see Drusus, at their backs</l>
               <l>a fearfull ambush rises. Farewell valours, </l>
               <l>excellent valours: o Rome,  where's thy wisdome?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006794">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> they are gone indeed,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006801">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> look out toward the army, </l>
               <l>I am heavie with these slaughters.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006811">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> 'tis the same still, </l>
               <l>cover'd with dust and fury. <stage>Enter the two daughters, 
with Junius,  Curius,  Decius,  and souldiers.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006824">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> bring 'em in, </l>
               <l>tie 'em,  and then unarm 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006834">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> valiant Romans, </l>
               <l>ye are welcome to your loves, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006844">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> your death, fools.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006851">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> we deserve 'em, </l>
               <l>and women do your worst.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006861">
               <speaker>1. Daug</speaker>
               <l> ye need not beg it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006868">
               <speaker>2. Daug</speaker>
               <l> which is kinde Junius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006875">
               <speaker>serv</speaker>
               <l> this.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006882">
               <speaker>2. Dau</speaker>
               <l> are you my sweet heart?</l>
               <l>It looks ill on't:how long is't,  pretty soul, </l>
               <l>since you and I first lov'd? Had we not reason</l>
               <l>to doat extreamly upon one another?</l>
               <l>How does my love? This is not he: my chicken</l>
               <l>could prate finely, sing a love-song.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006904">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> monster.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006911">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> oh, now it courts.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006918">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> arm'd with more malice</l>
               <l>then he that got thee has the divell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006928">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> good.</l>
               <l>Proceed, sweet chick.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006938">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I hate thee,  that's my last.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006945">
               <speaker>2. Daug</speaker>
               <l> nay, and ye love me, forward: no? Come sister, </l>
               <l>let's prick our answers on our arrows points, </l>
               <l>and make 'em laugh a little. Ye damn'd leachers, </l>
               <l>ye proud improvident fools,  have we now caught ye?</l>
               <l>Are ye i'th'noose? Since ye are such loving creatures, </l>
               <l>wee'll be your cupids: do ye see these arrows?</l>
               <l>Wee'll send 'em to your wanton livers,  goats.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006970">
               <speaker>1. Dau</speaker>
               <l> o how I'll trample on your hearts,  ye villains, </l>
               <l>ambitious salt-itcht slaves:Romes master sins, </l>
               <l>the mountain rams topt your hot mothers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000006983">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> dogs, </l>
               <l>to whose brave founders a salt whore gave suck; </l>
               <l>theeves,  honours hangmen,  do ye grin? Perdition</l>
               <l>take me for ever, if in my fell anger,  <stage>Enter Caratach</stage>
               </l>
               <l>I doe not out-doe all example.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007004">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> where, </l>
               <l>where are these ladies? Ye keep noble quarter, </l>
               <l>your mother thinks ye dead or taken; upon which, </l>
               <l>she will not move her battell. Sure these faces</l>
               <l>I have beheld and known, they are Roman leaders, </l>
               <l>how came they here?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007026">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> a trick sir, that we us'd, </l>
               <l>a certain policie conducted 'em</l>
               <l>unto our snare: we have done ye no small service; </l>
               <l>these us'd as we intend,  we are for th'battell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007042">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> as you intend? Taken by treachery?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007049">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> is't not allow'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007056">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> those that should gild our conquest, </l>
               <l>make up a battell worthie of our winning, </l>
               <l>catch'd up by craft?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007069">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> by any means that's lawfull.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007076">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> a womans wisedome in our triumphs? Out, </l>
               <l>out ye sluts,  ye follies;  from our swords</l>
               <l>filch our revenges basely? Arm again, gentlemen:</l>
               <l>souldiers, I charge ye help 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007092">
               <speaker>2. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> by-----uncle, </l>
               <l>we will have vengeance for our rapes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007102">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> by-----</l>
               <l>you should have kept your legs close then: dispatch there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007112">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> I will not off thus.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007119">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> he that stirs to execute, </l>
               <l>or she,  though it be your selves,  by him that got me, </l>
               <l>shall quickly feel mine anger:one great day given us, </l>
               <l>not to be snatch'd out of our hands but basely; </l>
               <l>and must we shame the gods from whence we have it, </l>
               <l>with setting snares for souldiers? I'll run away first, </l>
               <l>be hooted at, and children call me coward</l>
               <l>before I set up scales for victories:</l>
               <l>give 'em their swords.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007150">
               <speaker>2. Daug</speaker>
               <l> o gods.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007157">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> bear off the women</l>
               <l>unto their mother.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007167">
               <speaker>2. Dau</speaker>
               <l> one shot, gentle uncle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007174">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> one cut her fiddle-string:bear 'em off I say.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007181">
               <speaker>1. Dau</speaker>
               <l> the----take this fortune.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007188">
               <speaker>cara</speaker>
               <l> learn to spin, </l>
               <l>and curse your knotted hemp:goe gentlemen, </l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.daughters.</stage>
safely go off,  up to your troops:be wiser, </l>
               <l>there thank me like tall souldiers: I shall seek ye.<stage> exit Caratach.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007210">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> a noble worth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007217">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> well Junius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007224">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> pray ye no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007231">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> he blushes,  do not load him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007238">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> where's your love now? <stage> drums loud again.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007248">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> puffe,  there it flies: come, let's redeem our follies.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt. Junius,  Curius,  Decius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007261">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> awake,  sir;  yet the Roman bodie's whole, </l>
               <l>I see'em cleer again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007271">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> whole? 'Tis not possible:</l>
               <l>Drusus,  they must be lost.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007281">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> by-----they are whole, sir, </l>
               <l>and in brave doing; see, they wheel about</l>
               <l>to gain more ground.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007294">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> but see there Drusus,  see, </l>
               <l>see that huge battell moving from the mountains, </l>
               <l>their gilt coats shine like dragons scales,  their march</l>
               <l>like a rough tumbling storm;  see them, and view 'em.</l>
               <l>And then see Rome no more: say they faile; look, </l>
               <l>look where the armed carts stand; a new army:</l>
               <l>look how they hang like falling rocks, as murdring</l>
               <l>death rides in triumph Drusus:fell destruction</l>
               <l>lashes his fiery horse, and round about him</l>
               <l>his many thousand wayes to let out soules.</l>
               <l>Move me again when they charge,  when the mountain</l>
               <l>melts under their hot wheels, and from their ax'trees</l>
               <l>huge claps of thunder plough the ground before 'em, </l>
               <l>till then I'll dream what Rome was.<stage>Enter Swetonius,  Petillius,  Demetrius,  Macer.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007343">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> o bravely fought; honour till now nere show'd</l>
               <l>her golden face i'th'field. Like lions,  gentlemen, </l>
               <l>y'have held your heads up this day: where's yong Junius, </l>
               <l>Curius,  and Decius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007359">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> gone to heaven, I think,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007366">
               <speaker>sw</speaker>
               <l> their worths go with'em:breath a while: how do ye?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007373">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> wel,  some few scurvie wounds,  my heart's whole yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007380">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> would they would give us more ground.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007387">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> give? Wee'll have it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007394">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> have it? And hold it too, despight the divell.<stage>Enter Junius,  Decius,  Curius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007404">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> lead up th th'head, and line sure:the qs.battell</l>
               <l>begins to charge like wild-fire:where's the generall?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007414">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> oh, they are living yet. Come, my brave souldiers, </l>
               <l>come, let me powr Romes blessing on ye; live, </l>
               <l>live,  and lead armies all:ye bleed hard.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007427">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> best:</l>
               <l>wee shall appear the sterner to the foe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007437">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> more wounds,  more honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007444">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> lose no time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007451">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> away then, </l>
               <l>and stand this shock,  ye have stood the world.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007461">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> wee'll grow to't.</l>
               <l>Is not this better now then lowsie loving?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007471">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I am my self,  Petillius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007478">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> 'tis I love thee.  <stage>Exeunt.Romans.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Bonduca,  Caratach,  daughters,  Nennius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007491">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> charge 'em i'th'flanks:o ye have plaid the fool, </l>
               <l>the fool extremely, the mad fool.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007501">
               <speaker>Bon</speaker>
               <l> why cosin?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007508">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> the woman fool. Why did you give the word</l>
               <l>unto the carts to charge down, and our people</l>
               <l>in grosse before the enemie?we pay for't, </l>
               <l>our own swords cut out throats:why? ---on't, </l>
               <l>why do you offer to command? The divell, </l>
               <l>the divell, and his dam too, who bid you</l>
               <l>meddle in mens affairs?  <stage>Exeunt.queen,  and c.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007536">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> I'll help all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007543">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> home, </l>
               <l>home and spin woman,  spin, go spin, ye trifle.</l>
               <l>Open before there,  or all's ruine. How,  <stage> showts within</stage>
               </l>
               <l>now comes the tempest;  on our selves,  by---<stage> Victoria within</stage>
               </l>
               <l>o woman,  scurvie woman,  beastly woman.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007569">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> Victoria,  Victoria.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007576">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> how's that,  Drusus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007583">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> they win, they win,  they win;  oh look,  look,  look,  sir, </l>
               <l>for heavens sake look, the Britains fly, the Britains fly.</l>
               <l>Victoria. <stage>Enter Swetonius,  souldiers,  and captains.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007599">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> soft,  soft,  pursue if soft;  excellent souldiers, </l>
               <l>close, my brave fellows,  honourable Romans:</l>
               <l>oh cool thy mettle Junius,  they are ours, </l>
               <l>the world cannot redeem 'em: stern Petillius, </l>
               <l>govern the conquest nobly:soft,  good souldiers.<stage>Enter Bonduca,  daughters,  and Britains.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007621">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> shame,  whither flie ye,  ye unluckie Britains?</l>
               <l>Will ye creep into your mothers wombs again? Back</l>
               <l>cowards, </l>
               <l>hares,  fearfull hares,  doves in your angers; leave me?</l>
               <l>Leave your queen desolate? Her haplesse children<stage>Enter Caratach and Hengo</stage>
               </l>
               <l>to Roman rape again and fury?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007645">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> flie, ye buzzards, </l>
               <l>ye have wings enough, ye fear: get thee gone, woman, <stage> loud showt within</stage>
               </l>
               <l>shame tread upon thy heels: all's lost, all's lost, heark, </l>
               <l>heark how the Romans ring our knels. <stage> ext. Bond. and c.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007666">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> good uncle, </l>
               <l>let me go too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007676">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> no boy, thy fortune's mine, </l>
               <l>I must not leave thee; get behind me; shake not, <stage>Enter Petillius,  Junius,  Decius</stage>
               </l>
               <l>I'll breech ye, if ye do boy:come, brave Romans, </l>
               <l>all is not lost yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007694">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> now I'll thank thee,  Caratach. <stage> fight. Drums.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007704">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thou art a souldier: strike home,  home,  have at ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007711">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> his blows fall like huge sledges on an anvil.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007718">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> I am weary.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007725">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> so am i.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007732">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> send more swords to me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007739">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> let's sit and rest. <stage> sit down.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007749">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> what think ye now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007756">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> o Drusus, </l>
               <l>I have lost mine honour,  lost my name, </l>
               <l>lost all that was my light: these are true Romans, </l>
               <l>and I a Britain coward,  a base coward:</l>
               <l>guide me where nothing is but desolation, </l>
               <l>that I may never more behold the face</l>
               <l>of man,  or mankind know me:o blind fortune, </l>
               <l>hast thou abus'd me thus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007784">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> good sir,  be comforted; </l>
               <l>it was your wisdome rul'd ye; pray ye go home, </l>
               <l>your day is yet to come, when this great fortune</l>
               <l>shall be but soile unto it. <stage> retreat.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007803">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l>fool,  fool,  coward. <stage> exit Penyus and Drusus</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Swetonius,  Demetrius,  souldiers, 
    drums and colours.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007815">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> draw in,  draw in: wel have ye fought, and worthie</l>
               <l>Romes noble recompence; looke to your wounds, </l>
               <l>the ground is cold and hurtfull:the proud queen</l>
               <l>has got a fort, and there she and her daughters</l>
               <l>defie us once again. To morrow morning</l>
               <l>wee'll seek her out, and make her know, our fortunes</l>
               <l>stop at no stubborn walls:come, sons of honour, </l>
               <l>true vertues heirs:thus hatch'd with Britain blood, </l>
               <l>let's us march to rest, and set in gules like suns.</l>
               <l>Beat a soft march,  and each one ease his neighbours. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000007854">
               <head> Actus Quartus. Scaena Prima.</head>
            <stage>Enter Petillius,  Junius,  Decius,  Demetrius singing.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007861">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> smooth was his cheek, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007868">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> and his chin it was sleek, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007875">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> with whoop, he has done wooing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007882">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> Junius was this captains name, </l>
               <l>a lad for a lasses viewing, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007892">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> ful black his eye, andplump his thigh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007899">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> made up for loves pursuing:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007906">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> smooth was his check, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007913">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> and his chin it was sleek.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007920">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> with whoop, he has done wooing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007927">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> o my vex'd thief, art thou come home again?</l>
               <l>Are thy brains perfect?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007937">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> sound as bels.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007944">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> thy back-worm</l>
               <l>quiet,  and cast his sting,  boy?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007954">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> dead,  Petillius, </l>
               <l>dead to all folly, and now my anger only.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007964">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> why, that's wel said:hang cupid and his quiver, </l>
               <l>a drunken brawling boy:thy honour'd saint</l>
               <l>be thy ten shillings,  Junius; there's the money, </l>
               <l>and there's the ware; square dealing:this but sweats thee</l>
               <l>like a nesh nag, and makes thee look pin buttock'd; </l>
               <l>the other runs thee whining up and down</l>
               <l>like a pig in a storm, fils thy brains full of ballads, </l>
               <l>and shews thee like a long lent, thy brave body</l>
               <l>turn'd to a tail of green-fish without butter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000007995">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> when thou lov'st next, love a good cup of wine, </l>
               <l>a mistris for a king,  she leaps to kisse thee, </l>
               <l>her red and white's her own; she makes good blood, </l>
               <l>takes none away; what shee heats sleep can help, </l>
               <l>without a groping surgeon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008014">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I am counsell'd, </l>
               <l>and henceforth, when I doat again, ---</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008024">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> take heed, </l>
               <l>ye had almost paid for't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008034">
               <speaker>petil</speaker>
               <l> love no more great ladies, </l>
               <l>thou canst not step amisse then; there's no delight in 'em; </l>
               <l>all's in the whistling of their snatcht up silks; </l>
               <l>they're onely made for handsome view, not handling:</l>
               <l>their bodies of so weak and wash a temper, </l>
               <l>a rough-pac'd bed will shake 'em all to pieces; </l>
               <l>a tough hen puls their teeth out, tyres their souls; </l>
               <l>plenae rimarum sunt, they are full of rynnet, </l>
               <l>and take the skin off where they are tasted; shun 'em, </l>
               <l>they live in cullisses like rotten cocks</l>
               <l>stew'd to a tendernesse, that holds no tack:</l>
               <l>give me a thing I may crush.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008074">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> thou speak'st truly:</l>
               <l>the warres shall be my mistris now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008084">
               <speaker>petil</speaker>
               <l> well chosen, </l>
               <l>for she's a bownsing lasse,  she'll kisse thee at night,  boy, </l>
               <l>and break thy pate i'th' morning.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008097">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> yesterday</l>
               <l>I found those favours infinite.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008107">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> wench good enough, </l>
               <l>but that she talks too loud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008117">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> she talks to th'purpose, </l>
               <l>which never woman did yet:shee'll hold grapling, </l>
               <l>and he that layes on best, is her best servant:</l>
               <l>all other loves are meer catching of dotrels, </l>
               <l>stretching of legs out onely, and trim lazinesse.<stage>Enter swet. Curius and Macer</stage>
               </l>
               <l>here comes the generall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008141">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> I am glad I have found ye:</l>
               <l>are those come in yet that pursu'd bold Caratach?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008151">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> not yet sir, for I think they mean to lodge him; </l>
               <l>take him I know they dare not,  'twill be dangerous.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008161">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> then haste Petillius,  haste to Penyus, </l>
               <l>I fear the strong conceit of what disgrace</l>
               <l>h'as pull'd upon himself, will be his ruine:</l>
               <l>I fear his souldiers fury too; haste presently, </l>
               <l>I would not lose him for all Britain. Give him,  Petillius, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008180">
               <speaker>petil</speaker>
               <l> that that shall choak him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008187">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> all the noble counsell, </l>
               <l>his fault forgiven too, his place,  his honour, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008197">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> for me, I think, as handsome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008204">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> all the comfort; </l>
               <l>and tell the souldier,  'twas on our command</l>
               <l>hee drew not to the battell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008217">
               <speaker>petil</speaker>
               <l> I conceive sir, </l>
               <l>and will doe that shall cure all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008227">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> bring him with ye</l>
               <l>before the queens fort, and his forces with him, </l>
               <l>there you shall find us following of our conquest:</l>
               <l>make haste.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008243">
               <speaker>petil</speaker>
               <l> the best I may. <stage> exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008253">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> and noble gentlemen, </l>
               <l>up to your companies:wee'll presently</l>
               <l>upon the queens pursuit: there's nothing done</l>
               <l>till she be seiz'd,  without her nothing won.  <stage>Exeunt. short flourish.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000008274">
               <head> Scaena Secunda</head>
            <stage>Enter Caratach and Hengo.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008281">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> how does my boy?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008288">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> I would doe well, my heart's well; </l>
               <l>I doe not fear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008298">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> my good boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008305">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> I know,  uncle, </l>
               <l>we must all die; my little brother dy'd, </l>
               <l>I saw him die, and he dy'd smiling: sure, </l>
               <l>there's no great pain in't uncle. But pray tell me, </l>
               <l>whither must we goe when we are dead?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008324">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> strange questions</l>
               <l>why, to the blessed'st place boy:ever sweetnesse</l>
               <l>and happinesse dwels there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008337">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> will you come to me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008344">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> yes,  my sweet boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008351">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> mine aunt too,  and my cosins?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008358">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> all, my good childe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008365">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> no Romans,  uncle?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008372">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> no,  boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008379">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> I should be loth to meet them there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008386">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> no ill men, </l>
               <l>that live by violence,  and strong oppression, </l>
               <l>come thither:'t is for those the gods love, good men.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008399">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> why, then I care not when I go:for surely</l>
               <l>I am perswaded they love me:I never</l>
               <l>blasphem'd 'em,  uncle,  nor transgrest my parents; </l>
               <l>I always said my prayers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008415">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thou shalt go, then, </l>
               <l>indeed thou shalt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008425">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> when they please.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008432">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> that's my good boy.</l>
               <l>Art thou not weary,  Hengo?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008442">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> weary,  uncle?</l>
               <l>I have heard you say you have march'd all day in armour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008452">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I have,  boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008459">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> am not I your kinsman?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008466">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008473">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> and am not I as fully alli'd unto you</l>
               <l>in those brave things,  as blood?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008483">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thou art too tender.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008490">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> to go upon my legs? They were made to bear me:</l>
               <l>I can play twenty mile a day; I see no reason</l>
               <l>but,  to preserve my countrey and my self, </l>
               <l>I should march fourty.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008506">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> what, wouldst thou be</l>
               <l>living to wear a mans strength?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008516">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> why a Caratach, </l>
               <l>a Romane-hater,  a scourge sent from heaven <stage> drum</stage>
               </l>
               <l>to whip these proud theeves from our kingdom. Heark, </l>
               <l>heark,  uncle,  heark,  I hear a drum.<stage>Enter Judas and his people to the door.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008537">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> beat softly, </l>
               <l>softly,  I say;  they are here: who dare charge?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008547">
               <speaker>1 sould</speaker>
               <l> he</l>
               <l>that dares be knockt o'th'head:I'll not come neer him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008557">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> retire again, and watch then. How he stares</l>
               <l>h'as eyes would kill a dragon:mark the boy well; </l>
               <l>if we could take or kill him. A----on ye, </l>
               <l>how fierce ye look? See how he broods the boy; </l>
               <l>the divil dwells in's scabbard. Back, I say, </l>
               <l>apace,  apace,  h'as found us. <stage> they retire.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008582">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> do ye hunt us?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008589">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> uncle,  good uncle see, the thin starv'd rascal, </l>
               <l>the eating Romane,  see where he thrids the thickets:</l>
               <l>kill him, dear uncle,  kill him; one good blow</l>
               <l>to knock his brains into his breech:strike's head off, </l>
               <l>that I may pisse in's face.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008608">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> do ye make us foxes?</l>
               <l>Here,  hold my charging-staff,  and keep the place,  boy.</l>
               <l>I am at bay, and like a bull I'll bear me.</l>
               <l>Stand,  stand,  ye rogues,  ye squirrels. <stage> exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008627">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> now he pays 'em:</l>
               <l>o that I had a mans strength.<stage>Enter iudas,  and c.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008640">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> here's the boy; </l>
               <l>mine own, I thank my fortune.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008650">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> uncle,  uncle; </l>
               <l>famine is faln upon me,  uncle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008660">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> come, sir, </l>
               <l>yeeld willingly, your uncle's out of hearing; </l>
               <l>I'll tickle your young tail else.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008673">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> I defie thee, </l>
               <l>thou mock-made man of mat:charge home, sirha:</l>
               <l>hang thee,  base slave, thou shakest.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008686">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> upon my conscience</l>
               <l>the boy will beat me:how it looks,  how bravely, </l>
               <l>how confident the worm is:a scabb'd boy</l>
               <l>to handle me thus? Yeeld,  or I cut thy head off.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008702">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> thou dar'st not cut my finger:here't is,  touch it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008709">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> the boy speaks sword and buckler. Prethee yeeld,  boy:</l>
               <l>come,  here's an apple; yeeld.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008719">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> by---he fears me.</l>
               <l>I'll give you sharper language:when,  ye coward, </l>
               <l>when come ye up?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008732">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> if he should beat me---</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008739">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> when, sir?</l>
               <l>I long to kill thee; come,  thou canst not scape me, </l>
               <l>I have twenty ways to charge thee; twenty deaths</l>
               <l>attend my bloody staff.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008755">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> sure't is the devil, </l>
               <l>a dwarf,  devil in a doublet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008765">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> I have kill'd a captain,  sirha,  a brave captain, </l>
               <l>and when I have done, I have kickt him thus. Look here, </l>
               <l>see how I charge this staff.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008778">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> most certain</l>
               <l>this boy will cut my throat,  yet.<stage>Enter two souldiers,  running.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008791">
               <speaker>1. Sould</speaker>
               <l> flee,  flee,  he kills us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008798">
               <speaker>2. Sould</speaker>
               <l> he comes,  he comes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008805">
               <speaker>Iud</speaker>
               <l> the devil take the hindmost.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008812">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> run,  run,  ye rogues,  ye precious rogues,  ye rank rogues.</l>
               <l>A comes,  a comes,  a comes,  a comes:that's he, boys.</l>
               <l>What a brave cry they make?<stage>Enter Caratach,  with a head.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008828">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> how does my chicken?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008835">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> 'faith,  uncle,  grown a souldier,  a great souldier; </l>
               <l>for by the vertue of your charging-staff, </l>
               <l>and a strange fighting face I put upon't, </l>
               <l>I have outbrav'd hunger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008851">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> that's my boy, my sweet boy.</l>
               <l>Here,  here's a Romane's head for thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008861">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> good provision.</l>
               <l>Before I starve,  my sweet-fac'd gentleman, </l>
               <l>I'll trie your favour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008874">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> a right compleat souldier.</l>
               <l>Come,  chicken,  let's go seek some place of strength</l>
               <l>(the countrey's full of scouts) to rest a while in, </l>
               <l>thou wilt not else be able to endure.</l>
               <l>The journey to my countrey,  fruits,  and water, </l>
               <l>must be your food a while,  boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008896">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> any thing:</l>
               <l>I can eat mosse,  nay,  I can live on anger, </l>
               <l>to vex these Romanes. Let's be wary,  uncle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008909">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I warrant thee;  come chearfully.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008916">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> and boldly.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="40000008928">
               <head> Scaena Tertia.</head>
            <stage>Enter Penyus,  Drusus,  and Regulus.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008935">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> the souldier shall not grieve ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008942">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> pray ye forsake me; </l>
               <l>look not upon me, as ye love your honours; </l>
               <l>I am so cold a coward,  my infection</l>
               <l>will choke your vertues like a damp else.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008958">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> dear captain, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008965">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> most honour'd sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008972">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> most hated,  most abhor'd; </l>
               <l>say so,  and then ye know me,  nay,  ye please me.</l>
               <l>O my dear credit,  my dear credit.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008985">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> sure</l>
               <l>his minde is dangerous.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000008995">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> the good gods cure it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009002">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> my honour got thorow fire,  thorow stubborn,  breaches</l>
               <l>thorow battels that have been as hard to win as heaven, </l>
               <l>thorow death himself, in all his horrid trims, </l>
               <l>is gone for ever,  ever,  ever,  gentlemen, </l>
               <l>and now I am left to scornful tales and laughters, </l>
               <l>to hootings at,  pointing with fingers,  that's he, </l>
               <l>that's the brave gentleman forsook the battel, </l>
               <l>the most wise Penyus,  the disputing coward.</l>
               <l>O my good sword, break from my side, and kill mee; </l>
               <l>cut out the coward from my heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009036">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> ye are none.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009043">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> he lyes that says so: by----he lyes,  lyes basely, </l>
               <l>baser then I have done. Come,  souldiers,  seek me, </l>
               <l>I have robb'd ye of your vertues:justice,  seek me, </l>
               <l>I have broke my fair obedience,  lost:shame take me, </l>
               <l>take me, and swallow me, make ballads of me; </l>
               <l>shame,  endlesse shame:and pray do you forsake me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009065">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> what shall we do?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009072">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> good gentlemen forsake me:</l>
               <l>you were not wont to be commanded. Friends,  pray do it, </l>
               <l>and do not fear; for as I am a coward</l>
               <l>I will not hurt my self:when that minde takes me, </l>
               <l>I'll call to you, and ask your help. I dare not.<stage>Enter Petillius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009094">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> good morrow, gentlemen; where's the tribune?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009101">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009108">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> whence come ye, good Petillius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009115">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> from the general.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009122">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> with what, for heavens sake?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009129">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> with good counsel,  Drusus, </l>
               <l>and love,  to comfort him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009139">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> good Regulus</l>
               <l>step to the souldier, and allay his anger; </l>
               <l>for he is wilde as winter.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.Drusius and Regulus.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009158">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> o,  are ye there? Have at ye. Sure he's dead, </l>
               <l>it cannot be he dare out live this fortune:</l>
               <l>he must die,  'tis most necessary; men expect it; </l>
               <l>and thought of life in him,  goes beyond coward.</l>
               <l>Forsake the field so basely?fie upon't:</l>
               <l>so poorly to betray his worth? So coldly</l>
               <l>to cut all credit from the souldier? Sure</l>
               <l>if this man mean to live, as I should think it</l>
               <l>beyond belief, he must retire where never</l>
               <l>the name of Rome, the voice of arms, or honour</l>
               <l>was known or heard of yet:he's certain dead, </l>
               <l>or strongly means it; he's no souldier else, </l>
               <l>no Romane in him; all he has done, but outside, </l>
               <l>fought either drunk or desperate. Now he rises.</l>
               <l>How does lord Penyus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009207">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> as ye see.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009214">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I am glad on't; </l>
               <l>continue so still. The lord general, </l>
               <l>the valiant general,  great Swetonius-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009227">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> no more of me is spoken; my name's perish'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009234">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> he that commanded fortune and the day</l>
               <l>by his own valour and discretion, </l>
               <l>when,  as some say,  Penyus refused to come, </l>
               <l>but I believe 'em not, sent me to see ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009250">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> ye are welcom; and pray see me;  see me well, </l>
               <l>ye shall not see me long.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009260">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I hope so,  Penyus; </l>
               <l>the gods defend,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009270">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> see me, and understand me:this is he</l>
               <l>left to fill up your triumph; he that basely</l>
               <l>whistled his honour off to th'winde; that coldly</l>
               <l>shrunk in his politick head,  when Rome like reapers</l>
               <l>sweat blood,  and spirit, for a glorious harvest, </l>
               <l>and bound it up, and brought it off:that fool, </l>
               <l>that having gold and copper offer'd him, </l>
               <l>refus'd the wealth, and took the waste: that souldier</l>
               <l>that being courted by loud fame and fortune, </l>
               <l>labour in one hand, that propounds us gods, </l>
               <l>and in the other,  glory that creats us, </l>
               <l>yet durst doubt,  and be damned.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009310">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> it was an errour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009317">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> a foul one,  and a black one.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009324">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> yet the blackest</l>
               <l>may be washt white again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009334">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> never.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009341">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> your leave,  sir, </l>
               <l>and I beseech ye note me:for I love ye, </l>
               <l>and bring along all comfort:are we gods, </l>
               <l>alli'd to no infirmities? Are our natures</l>
               <l>more then mens natures?when we slip a little</l>
               <l>out of the way of vertue, are we lost?</l>
               <l>Is there no medicine called sweet mercie?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009366">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> none,  Petillius; </l>
               <l>there is no mercie in mankinde can reach me, </l>
               <l>nor is it fit it should; I have sinn'd beyond it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009379">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> forgivenesse meets with all faults, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009386">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> 'tis all faults, </l>
               <l>all sins I can commit,  to be forgiven:</l>
               <l>'tis losse of whole man in me, my discretion</l>
               <l>to be so stupid, to arrive at pardon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009402">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> o but the general-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009409">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> he's a brave gentleman, </l>
               <l>a valiant, and a loving; and I dare say</l>
               <l>he would, as far as honour durst direct him, </l>
               <l>make even with my fault: but 'tis not honest, </l>
               <l>nor in his power: examples that may nourish</l>
               <l>neglect and disobedience in whole bodies, </l>
               <l>and totter the estates and faiths of armies, </l>
               <l>must not be plaid withal; nor out of pitie</l>
               <l>make a general forget his duty:</l>
               <l>nor dare I hope more from him then is worthy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009443">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> what would ye do?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009450">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009457">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> so would sullen children, </l>
               <l>women that want their wils,  slaves,  disobedient, </l>
               <l>that fear the law,  die. Fie,  great captain;  you</l>
               <l>a man to rule men,  to have thousand lives</l>
               <l>under your regiment, and let your passion</l>
               <l>betray your reason? I bring you all forgivenesse, </l>
               <l>the noblest kinde commends,  your place,  your honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009482">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> prethee no more;  'tis foolish:didst not thou?</l>
               <l>By---thou didst, I over-heard thee,  there, </l>
               <l>there where thou standst now, deliver me for rascal, </l>
               <l>poor,  dead,  cold coward,  miserable,  wretched, </l>
               <l>if I out-liv'd this ruine?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009501">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> i?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009508">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> and thou didst it nobly.</l>
               <l>Like a true man, a souldier:and I thank thee, </l>
               <l>I thanke thee,  good Petillius; thus I thank thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009521">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> since ye are so justly made up,  let me tell ye</l>
               <l>'tis fit ye die indeed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009531">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> o how thou lovest me</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009538">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> for say he had forgiven ye; say the peoples whispers</l>
               <l>were tame again, the time run out for wonder, </l>
               <l>what must your own command think,  from whose</l>
               <l>swords</l>
               <l>ye have taken off the edges, from whose valours</l>
               <l>the due and recompence of arms; nay, made it doubtful</l>
               <l>whether they knew obedience?must not these kill ye?</l>
               <l>Say they are won to pardon ye, by meer miracle</l>
               <l>brought to forgive ye; what old valiant souldier, </l>
               <l>what man that loves to fight,  and fight for Rome, </l>
               <l>will ever follow you more?dare ye know these ventures?</l>
               <l>If so, I bring ye comfort; dare ye take it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009578">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> no,  no,  Petillius,  no.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009585">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> if your minde serve ye, </l>
               <l>ye may live still; but how? Yet pardon me, </l>
               <l>you may outwear all too; but when? And certain</l>
               <l>there is a mercy for each fault, if tamely</l>
               <l>a man will take't upon conditions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009604">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> no, by no means:I am onely thinking now, sir, </l>
               <l>(for I am resolved to go)of a most base death, </l>
               <l>fitting the basenesse of my fault. I'll hang, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009617">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> ye shall not; y'are a gentleman I honour, </l>
               <l>I would else flatter ye,  and force ye live, </l>
               <l>which is far baser. Hanging? 'Tis a dogs death, </l>
               <l>an end for slaves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009633">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> the fitter for my basenesse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009640">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> besides, the man that's hang'd, preaches his end, </l>
               <l>and sits a signe for all the world to gape at.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009650">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> that's true:I'll take a fitter poison.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009657">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> no, </l>
               <l>'tis equal ill; the death of rats,  and women, </l>
               <l>lovers,  and lazie boys, that fear correction.</l>
               <l>Die like a man.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009673">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> why my sword then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009680">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> i,  if your sword be sharp,  sir, </l>
               <l>there's nothing under heaven that's like your sword; </l>
               <l>your sword's a death indeed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009693">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> it shall be sharp,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009700">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> why mithridates was an arrant asse</l>
               <l>to die by poison, if all bosphorus</l>
               <l>could lend him swords:your sword must do the deed:</l>
               <l>'tis shame to die choak'd, fame to die and bleed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009716">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> thou hast confirmed me:and, my good Petillius, </l>
               <l>tell me no more I may live.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009726">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> 't was my commission; </l>
               <l>but now I see ye in a nobler way, </l>
               <l>a way to make all even.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009739">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> fare-well, captain:</l>
               <l>be a good man, and fight well:be obedient:</l>
               <l>command thy self, and then thy men. Why shakest thou?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009752">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I do not, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009759">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> I would thou hadst,  Petillius:</l>
               <l>I would finde something to forsake the world with</l>
               <l>worthy the man that dies:a kinde of earth-quake</l>
               <l>thorow all stern valours but mine own.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009775">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I feel now</l>
               <l>a kinde of trembling in me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009785">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> keep it still, </l>
               <l>as thou lov'st vertue, keep it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009795">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> and brave captain, </l>
               <l>the great and honoured Penyus.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009805">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> that again:</l>
               <l>o how it heightens me again,  Petillius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009815">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> most excellent commander.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009822">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> those were mine, </l>
               <l>mine,  onely mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009832">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> they are still.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009839">
               <speaker>Pen</speaker>
               <l> then to keep 'em</l>
               <l>for ever falling more,  have at ye, heavens, </l>
               <l>ye everlasting powers,  I am yours: the work's done, </l>
               <l>that neither fire, nor melting envie</l>
               <l>shall ever conquer. Carry my last words</l>
               <l>to the great general:kisse his hands,  and say, </l>
               <l>my soul I give to heaven,  my fault to justice</l>
               <l>which I have done upon my self:my vertue, </l>
               <l>if ever there was any in poor Penyus, </l>
               <l>made more, and happier,  light on him. I faint.</l>
               <l>And where there is a foe,  I wish him fortune.</l>
               <l>I die:lie lightly on my ashes,  gentle earth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009879">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> and on my sin. Fare-well,  great Penyus, <stage> noise within</stage>
               </l>
               <l>the souldier is in fury. Now I am glad</l>
               <l>'tis done before he comes. This way, for me, </l>
               <l>the way of toil; for thee,  the way of honour. <stage> exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Drusus and Regulus,  with souldiers.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009903">
               <speaker>sould</speaker>
               <l> kill him,  kill him,  kill him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009910">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> what will ye do?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009917">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> good souldiers,  honest souldiers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009924">
               <speaker>sould</speaker>
               <l> kill him,  kill him,  kill him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009931">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> kill us first; we command too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009938">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> valiant souldiers, </l>
               <l>consider but whose life ye seek. O Drusus, </l>
               <l>bid him be gone, he dies else. Shall Rome say</l>
               <l>(ye most approved souldiers) her dear children</l>
               <l>devoured the fathers of the fights? Shall rage</l>
               <l>and stubborn fury guide those swords to slaughter, </l>
               <l>to slaughter of their own, to civil ruine?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009963">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> o let 'em in: all's done,  all's ended,  Regulus, </l>
               <l>Penyus has found his last eclipse. Come,  souldiers, </l>
               <l>come,  and behold your miseries:come bravely, </l>
               <l>full of your mutinious and bloody angers, </l>
               <l>and here bestow your darts. O onely Romane, </l>
               <l>o father of the wars.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="50000009985">
               <speaker>Reg</speaker>
               <l> why stand ye stupid?</l>
               <l>Where be your killing furies? Whose sword now</l>
               <l>shall first be sheath'd in Penyus? Do ye weep?</l>
               <l>Howl out, ye wretches,  ye have cause:howl ever.</l>
               <l>Who shall now lead ye fortunate? Whose valour</l>
               <l>preserve ye to the glory of your countrey?</l>
               <l>Who shall march out before ye, coy'd and courted</l>
               <l>by all the mistrisses of war,  care,  counsel, </l>
               <l>quick-ey'd experience,  and victory twin'd to him?</l>
               <l>Who shall beget ye deeds beyond inheritance</l>
               <l>to speak your names, and keep your honours living, </l>
               <l>when children fail, and time that takes all with him, </l>
               <l>build houses for ye to oblivion?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010028">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> o ye poor desperate fools:no more now,  souldiers; </l>
               <l>go home,  and hang your arms up;  let rust rot 'em; </l>
               <l>and humble your stern valours to soft prayers; </l>
               <l>for ye have sunk the frame of all your vertues; </l>
               <l>the sun that warm'd your bloods is set for ever:</l>
               <l>I'll kisse thy honour'd cheek. Fare well,  great Penyus, </l>
               <l>thou thunder-bolt,  fare-well. Take up the body:</l>
               <l>to morrow morning to the camp convey it.</l>
               <l>There to receive due ceremonies. That eye</l>
               <l>that blindes himself with weeping,  gets most glory.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.with a dead march.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="400000010070">
               <head> Scaena Quarta.</head>
            <stage>Enter Swetonius,  Junius,  Decius,  Demetrius,  Curius,  and
souldiers: Bonduca,  two daughters,  and Nennius, 
above. Drum and colours.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010077">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> bring up the catapults and shake the wall, </l>
               <l>we will not be out-brav'd thus.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010087">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> shake the earth, </l>
               <l>ye cannot shake our souls. Bring up your rams, </l>
               <l>and with their armed heads,  make the fort totter, </l>
               <l>ye do but rock us into death. <stage> exit Nennius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010106">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> see sir, </l>
               <l>see the icenian queen in all her glory</l>
               <l>from the strong battlements proudly appearing, </l>
               <l>as if she meant to give us lashes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010122">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> yeeld,  queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010129">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> I am unacquainted with that language,  Roman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010136">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> yeeld, honour'd lady,  and expect our mercie, <stage> exit Decius</stage>
               </l>
               <l>we love thy noblenesse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010148">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> I thank ye,  ye say well; </l>
               <l>but mercie and love are sins in Rome and hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010158">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> ye cannot scape our strength; ye must yeeld,  ladie, </l>
               <l>ye must adore and fear the power of Rome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010168">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> if Rome be earthly, why should any knee</l>
               <l>with bending adoration worship her?</l>
               <l>She's vitious; and your partiall selves confesse, </l>
               <l>aspires the height of all impietie:</l>
               <l>therefore 'tis fitter I should reverence</l>
               <l>the thatched houses where the Britains dwell</l>
               <l>in carelesse mirth, where the blest houshold gods</l>
               <l>see nought but chaste and simple puritie.</l>
               <l>'Tis not high power that makes a place divine, </l>
               <l>nor that the men from gods derive their line.</l>
               <l>But sacred thoughts in holy bosoms stor'd, </l>
               <l>make people noble, and the place ador'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010208">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> beat the wall deeper.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010215">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> beat it to the center, </l>
               <l>we will not sink one thought.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010225">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> I'll make ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010232">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> no.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010239">
               <speaker>2. Dau</speaker>
               <l> o mother,  these are fearfull hours:speak gently<stage>Enter Petillius</stage>
               </l>
               <l>to these fierce men, they will afford ye pitie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010251">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> pitie? Thou fearful girl;  'tis for those wretches</l>
               <l>that miserie makes tame. Wouldst thou live lesse?</l>
               <l>Wast not thou born a princesse? Can my blood, </l>
               <l>and thy brave fathers spirit,  suffer in thee</l>
               <l>so base a separation from thy self, </l>
               <l>as mercie from these tyrants? Thou lov'st lust sure, </l>
               <l>and long'st to prostitute thy youth and beautie</l>
               <l>to common slaves for bread. Say they had mercie; </l>
               <l>the divel a relenting conscience:</l>
               <l>the lives of kings rest in their diadems, </l>
               <l>which to their bodies lively souls do give, </l>
               <l>and ceasing to be kings,  they cease to live.</l>
               <l>Show such another fear,  and-----</l>
               <l>I'll fling thee to their furie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010297">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> he is dead then?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010304">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I think so certainly; yet all my means,  sir, </l>
               <l>even to the hazzard of my life---</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010314">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> no more:</l>
               <l>wee must not seem to mourn here.<stage>Enter Decius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010327">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> there's a breach made, </l>
               <l>is it your will we charge,  sir?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010337">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> once more mercie, </l>
               <l>mercie to all that yeeld.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010347">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> I scorn to answer:</l>
               <l>speak to him girle; and hear thy sister.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010357">
               <speaker>1. Daugh</speaker>
               <l> generall, </l>
               <l>hear me,  and mark me well, and look upon me</l>
               <l>directly in my face,  my womans face, </l>
               <l>whose onely beautie is the hate it bears ye; </l>
               <l>see with thy narrowest eyes,  thy sharpest wishes, </l>
               <l>into my soul, and see what there inhabits; </l>
               <l>see if one fear, one shadow of a terrour, </l>
               <l>one palenesse dare appear but from my anger, </l>
               <l>to lay hold on your mercies. No, ye fools, </l>
               <l>poor fortunes fools,  we were not born for triumphs, </l>
               <l>to follow your gay sports,  and fill your slaves</l>
               <l>with hoots and acclamations.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010397">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> brave behaviour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010404">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> the children of as great as Rome,  as noble, </l>
               <l>our names before her, and our deeds her envie; </l>
               <l>must we gild ore your conquest,  make your state, </l>
               <l>that is not fairly strong, but fortunate?</l>
               <l>No,  no,  ye Romanes,  we have ways to scape ye, </l>
               <l>to make yee poor again, indeed our prisoners, </l>
               <l>and stick our triumphs full.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010429">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> 's death, I shall love her.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010436">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> to torture ye with suffering,  like our slaves; </l>
               <l>to make ye curse our patience,  wish the world</l>
               <l>were lost again, to win us onely, and esteem</l>
               <l>the end of all ambitions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010452">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> do ye wonder?</l>
               <l>We'll make our monuments in spite of fortune, </l>
               <l>in spight of all your eagles wings:we'll work</l>
               <l>a pitch above ye; and from our height we'll stoop</l>
               <l>as fearlesse of your bloody fears; and fortunate, </l>
               <l>as if we prey'd on heartlesse doves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010474">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> strange stiffnesse.</l>
               <l>Decius,  go charge the breach. <stage> exit Decius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010487">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> charge it home,  Romane, </l>
               <l>we shall deceive thee else. Where's Nennius?<stage>Enter Nennius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010500">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> they have made a mighty breach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010507">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> stick in thy body, </l>
               <l>and make it good but half an hour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010517">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> I'll do it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010524">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> and then be sure to die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010531">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> it shall go hard else.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010538">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> fare well with all my heart;  we shall meet yonder, </l>
               <l>where few of these must come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010548">
               <speaker>Nen</speaker>
               <l> gods take thee,  lady.<stage> exit Nennius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010558">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> bring up the swords,  and poison.<stage>Enter one with swords,  and a great cup.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010568">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> o my fortune</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010575">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> how,  how,  ye whore?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010582">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> good mother,  nothing to offend ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010589">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> here,  wench:</l>
               <l>behold us,  Romanes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010599">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> mercy yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010606">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> no talking:</l>
               <l>puff;  there goes all your pitie. Come,  short prayers, </l>
               <l>and let's dispatch the businesse:you begin, </l>
               <l>shrink not;  I'll see ye do't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010622">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> o gentle mother, </l>
               <l>o Romanes,  o my heart;  I dare not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010632">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> woman,  woman, </l>
               <l>unnatural woman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010642">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> o perswade her,  Romanes:</l>
               <l>alas,  I am young,  and would live. Noble mother, </l>
               <l>can ye kill that ye gave life? Are my yeers</l>
               <l>fit for destruction?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010658">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> yeeld,  and be a queen still, </l>
               <l>a mother,  and a friend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010668">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> ye talk:come,  hold it, </l>
               <l>and put it home.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010678">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> fie,  sister,  fie, </l>
               <l>what would you live to be?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010688">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> a whore still.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010695">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> mercie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010702">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> hear her,  thou wretched woman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010709">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> mercie,  mother:</l>
               <l>o whither will you send me? I was once</l>
               <l>your darling,  your delight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010722">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> o gods, </l>
               <l>fear in my family? Do it,  and nobly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010732">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> o do not frown then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010739">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> do it,  worthy sister:</l>
               <l>'tis nothing,  'tis a pleasure;  we'll go with ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010749">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> o if I knew but whither.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010756">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> to the blessed, </l>
               <l>where we shall meet our father.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010766">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> woman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010773">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> talk not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010780">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> where nothing but true joy is.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010787">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> that's a good wench, mine own sweet girl;  put</l>
               <l>it close to thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010797">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> o comfort me still, for heavens sake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010804">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> where eternal</l>
               <l>our youths are,  and our beauties; where no wars come, </l>
               <l>nor lustful slaves to ravish us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010817">
               <speaker>2 daugh</speaker>
               <l> that steels me:</l>
               <l>a long farewel to this world.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010827">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> good:I'll help thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010834">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> the next is mine.</l>
               <l>Shew me a Romane lady in all your stories, </l>
               <l>dare do this for her honour:they are cowards, </l>
               <l>eat coals like compell'd cats: your great saint lucrece</l>
               <l>di'd not for honour;  tarquin topt her well, </l>
               <l>and mad she could not hold him,  bled.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010856">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> by---</l>
               <l>I am in love:I would give an hundred pound now</l>
               <l>but to lie with this womans behaviour. O the devil.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010869">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> ye shall see me example. All your Rome, </l>
               <l>if I were proud, and lov'd ambition; </l>
               <l>if I were lustful, all your ways of pleasure; </l>
               <l>if I were greedie, all the wealth ye conquer--</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010885">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> make haste.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010892">
               <speaker>1 daugh</speaker>
               <l> I will. Could not intice to live</l>
               <l>but two short hours this frailty: would ye learn</l>
               <l>how to die bravely,  Romanes,  to fling off</l>
               <l>this case of flesh, lose all your cares for ever?</l>
               <l>Live as we have done,  well,  and fear the gods, </l>
               <l>hunt honour, and not nations with your swords, </l>
               <l>keep your mindes humble, your devotions high; </l>
               <l>so shall ye learn the noblest part, to die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010920">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> I come,  wench; to ye all fates hang-men; you</l>
               <l>that ease the aged destinies,  and cut</l>
               <l>the threds of kingdoms,  as they draw 'em; here, </l>
               <l>here's a draught would ask no lesse then Caesar</l>
               <l>to pledge it for the glories sake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010939">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> great lady.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010946">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> make up your own conditions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010953">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> so we will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010960">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> stay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010967">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> stay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010974">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> be any thing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000010981">
               <speaker>Bond</speaker>
               <l> a saint,  Swetonius, </l>
               <l>when thou shalt fear,  and die like a slave. Ye fools, </l>
               <l>ye should have ti'd up death first,  when ye conquer'd, </l>
               <l>ye sweat for us in vain else: see him here, </l>
               <l>he's ours still,  and our friend; laughs at your pities; </l>
               <l>and we command him with as easie reins</l>
               <l>as do our enemies. I feel the poison.</l>
               <l>Poor vanquish'd Romanes,  with what matchlesse tortures</l>
               <l>could I now rack ye? But I pitie ye, </l>
               <l>desiring to die quiet: nay, so much</l>
               <l>I hate to prosecute my victory, </l>
               <l>that I will give ye counsel ere I die.</l>
               <l>If you will keep your laws and empire whole, </l>
               <l>place in your Romane flesh a Britain soul.<stage>Enter Decius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011030">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> desperate and strange.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011037">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> 'tis won,  sir,  and the Britains</l>
               <l>all put to th'sword.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011047">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> give her fair funeral; </l>
               <l>she was truely noble,  and a queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011057">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> -----take it, </l>
               <l>a love-mange grown upon me? What,  a spirit?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011067">
               <speaker>iun</speaker>
               <l> I am glad of this,  I have found ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011074">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> in my belly, </l>
               <l>o how it tumbles?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011084">
               <speaker>iun</speaker>
               <l> ye good gods,  I thank ye.<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="400000011096">
               <head> Actus Quintus. Scaena Prima.</head>
            <stage>Enter Caratach upon a rock,  and Hengo by him,  sleeping.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011103">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thus we afflicted Britains climb for safeties, </l>
               <l>and to avoid our dangers,  seek destructions, </l>
               <l>thus we awake to sorrows. O thou woman, </l>
               <l>thou agent for adversities,  what curses</l>
               <l>this day belong to thy improvidence?</l>
               <l>To britanie by thy means,  what sad millions</l>
               <l>of widows weeping eyes? The strong mans valour</l>
               <l>thou hast betraid to fury; the childes fortune</l>
               <l>to fear, and want of friends:whose pieties</l>
               <l>might wipe his mournings off,  and build his sorrows</l>
               <l>a house of rest by his blest ancestors:</l>
               <l>the virgins thou hast rob'd of all their wishes, </l>
               <l>blasted their blowing hopes,  turn'd their songs, </l>
               <l>their mirthful marriage-songs to funerals, </l>
               <l>the land thou hast left a wildernesse of wretches.</l>
               <l>The boy begins to stir:thy safety made, </l>
               <l>would my soul were in heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011158">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> o noble uncle, </l>
               <l>look out;  I dream'd we were betraid.<stage> a soft dead march within.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011171">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> no harm, boy; </l>
               <l>'tis but thy emptinesse that breeds these fancies; </l>
               <l>thou shalt have meat anon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011184">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> a little, uncle, </l>
               <l>and I shall hold out bravely. What are those?</l>
               <l>Look,  uncle,  look,  those multitudes that march there?</l>
               <l>They come upon us stealing by.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011200">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I see 'em; </l>
               <l>and prethee be not fearful.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011210">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> now ye hate me, </l>
               <l>would I were dead.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011220">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thou know'st I love thee dearly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011227">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> did I ere shrink yet,  uncle? Were I a man now, </l>
               <l>I should be angry with ye.<stage>Enter Drusus,  Regulus,  and souldiers,  with Penyus herse,  drums and colours.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011240">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> my sweet chicken, </l>
               <l>see,  thy have reach'd us,  as it seems they bear</l>
               <l>some souldiers body,  by their solemn gestures, </l>
               <l>and sad solemnities; it well appears too</l>
               <l>to be of eminence. Most worthy souldiers, </l>
               <l>let me intreat your knowledge to inform me</l>
               <l>what noble body that is which you bear</l>
               <l>with such a sad and ceremonious grief, </l>
               <l>as if ye meant to woo the world and nature</l>
               <l>to be in love with death? Most honourable</l>
               <l>excellent Romanes,  by your ancient valours, </l>
               <l>as ye love fame,  resolve me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011280">
               <speaker>sould</speaker>
               <l> 'tis the body</l>
               <l>of the great captain Penyus, by himself</l>
               <l>made cold and spiritlesse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011293">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> o stay,  ye Romanes, </l>
               <l>by the religion which you owe those gods</l>
               <l>that lead ye on to victories,  by those glories</l>
               <l>which made even pride a vertue in ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011309">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> stay:</l>
               <l>what's thy will,  Caratach?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011319">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> set down the body, </l>
               <l>the body of the noblest of all Romanes, </l>
               <l>as ye expect an offering at your graves</l>
               <l>from your friends sorrows,  set it down a while, </l>
               <l>that with your griefs an enemy may mingle:</l>
               <l>a noble enemy that loves a souldier; </l>
               <l>and lend a tear to vertue:even your foes, </l>
               <l>your wild foes,  as you call'd us, are yet stor'd</l>
               <l>with fair affections,  our hearts fresh, our spirits, </l>
               <l>though sometimes stubborn, yet when vertue dies, </l>
               <l>soft and relenting as a virgins prayers.</l>
               <l>O set it down.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011359">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> set down the body,  souldiers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011366">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thou hallowed relique,  thou rich diamond</l>
               <l>cut with thine own dust;  thou for whose wide fame</l>
               <l>the world appears too narrow,  mans all thoughts, </l>
               <l>had they all tongues,  too silent;  thus I bow</l>
               <l>to thy most honour'd ashes; though an enemy, </l>
               <l>yet friend to all thy worths: sleep peaceably; </l>
               <l>happinesse crown thy soul, and in thy earth</l>
               <l>some lawrel fix his seat,  there grow, and flourish, </l>
               <l>and make thy grave an everlasting triumph.</l>
               <l>Fare well all glorious wars,  now thou art gone, </l>
               <l>and honest arms adieu:all noble battels</l>
               <l>maintain'd in thirst of honour, not of blood, </l>
               <l>fare well for ever.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011409">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> was this Romane,  uncle, </l>
               <l>so good a man?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011419">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thou never knew'st thy father.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011426">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> he di'd before I was born.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011433">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> this worthy Romane</l>
               <l>was such another piece of endlesse honour, </l>
               <l>such a brave soul dwelt in him:their proportions</l>
               <l>and faces were not much unlike,  boy:excellent natures, </l>
               <l>see how it works into his eyes, mine own boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011452">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> the multitudes of these men, and their fortunes, </l>
               <l>could never make me fear yet:one mans goodnesse-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011462">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> o now thou pleasest me: weep still, my childe, </l>
               <l>as if thou saw'st me dead; with such a flux</l>
               <l>or flood of sorrow:still thou pleasest me.</l>
               <l>And worthy souldiers,  pray receive these pledges, </l>
               <l>these hatchments of our griefs, and grace us so much</l>
               <l>to place 'em on his hearse. Now if ye please, </l>
               <l>bear off the noble burden; raise his pile</l>
               <l>high as olympus, making heaven to wonder</l>
               <l>to see a star upon earth outshining theirs.</l>
               <l>And ever loved,  ever living be</l>
               <l>thy honoured and most sacred memory.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011499">
               <speaker>Dru</speaker>
               <l> thou hast done honestly,  good Caratach, </l>
               <l>and when thou diest,  a thousand vertuous Romanes</l>
               <l>shall sing thy soul to heaven. Now march on, souldiers.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt. A dead march.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011518">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> now dry thine eyes,  my boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011525">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> are they all gone?</l>
               <l>I could have wept this hour yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011535">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> come,  take cheer, </l>
               <l>and raise thy spirit,  childe:if but this day</l>
               <l>thou canst bear out thy faintnesse,  the night coming</l>
               <l>I'll fashion our escape.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011551">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> pray fear not me; </l>
               <l>indeed I am very heartie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011561">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> be so still; </l>
               <l>his mischiefs lessen, that controls his ill.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="400000011579">
               <head> Scaena Secunda.</head>
            <stage>Enter Petillius.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011586">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> what do I ail,  i'th'name of heaven? I did but see her, </l>
               <l>and see her die: she stinks by this time strongly, </l>
               <l>abominably stinks:she was a woman, </l>
               <l>a thing I never car'd for:but to die so, </l>
               <l>so confidently,  bravely,  strongly; o the devil, </l>
               <l>I have the bots,  by--;  she scorn'd us, strangely, </l>
               <l>all we could do, or durst do; threatned us</l>
               <l>with such a noble anger, and so governed</l>
               <l>with such a fiery spirit---; the plain bots; </l>
               <l>a---upon the bots,  the love-bots:hang me, </l>
               <l>hang me even out o'th'way, directly hang me.</l>
               <l>O pennie pipers,  and most painful penners</l>
               <l>of bountiful new ballads,  what a subject, </l>
               <l>what a sweet subject for your silver sounds, </l>
               <l>is crept upon ye?<stage>Enter Junius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011638">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> here he is; have at him. <stage> sings</stage>
               </l>
               <l>she set the sword unto her brest, </l>
               <l>great pitie it was to see, </l>
               <l>that three drops of her life-warm blood, </l>
               <l>run trickling down her knee.</l>
               <l>Art thou there,  bonny boy? And ifaith how dost thou?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011662">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> well,  gramercie,  how dost thou? H'as found me, </l>
               <l>sented me out:the shame the devil ow'd me, </l>
               <l>h'as kept his day with. And what news,  Junius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011675">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> it was an old tale ten thousand times told, </l>
               <l>of a young lady was turn'd into mold, </l>
               <l>her life was lovely, her death it was bold.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011688">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> a cruel rogue; now h'as drawn pursue on me, </l>
               <l>he hunts me like a devil. No more singing; </l>
               <l>thou hast got a cold:come, let's go drink some sack,  boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011701">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> ha,  ha,  ha,  ha,  ha,  ha.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011708">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> why dost thou laugh?</l>
               <l>What mares nest hast thou found?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011718">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> ha,  ha,  ha.</l>
               <l>I cannot laugh alone:Decius,  Demetrius, </l>
               <l>Curius: o my sides. Ha,  ha,  ha,  ha, </l>
               <l>the strangest jest.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011734">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> prethee no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011741">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> the admirablest fooling.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011748">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> thou art the prettiest fellow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011755">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> sirs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011762">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> why Junius, </l>
               <l>prethee away, sweet Junius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011772">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> let me sing then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011779">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> whoa,  here's a stir now:sing a song o'six pence, </l>
               <l>by-----(if)prethee;  -----on't:Junius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011789">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I must either sing,  or laugh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011796">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> and what's your reason?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011803">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> what's that to you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011810">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> and I must whistle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011817">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> do so.</l>
               <l>O,  I hear 'em coming.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011827">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I have a little businesse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011834">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> thou shalt not go,  believe it:what a gentleman</l>
               <l>of thy sweet conversation?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011844">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> captain Junius, </l>
               <l>sweet captain, let me go with all celerity; </l>
               <l>things are not always one:and do not question, </l>
               <l>nor jeer,  nor gybe:none of your doleful ditties, </l>
               <l>nor your sweet conversation:you will finde then</l>
               <l>I may be anger'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011866">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> by no means,  Petillius; </l>
               <l>anger a man that never knew passion?</l>
               <l>'Tis most impossible:a noble captain, </l>
               <l>a wise and generous gentleman?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011882">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> tom puppie, </l>
               <l>leave this way to abuse me:I have found ye, </l>
               <l>but for your mothers sake I will forgive ye.</l>
               <l>Your subtil understanding may discover</l>
               <l>(as you think) some trim toy to make you merry; </l>
               <l>some straw to tickle ye; but do not trust to't; </l>
               <l>y'are a young man, and may do well; be sober; </l>
               <l>carry your self discreetly.<stage>Enter Decius,  Demetrius,  Curius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011913">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> yes forsooth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011920">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> how does the brave Petillius?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011927">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> monstrous merry:</l>
               <l>we two were talking what a kinde of thing</l>
               <l>I was when I was in love; what a strange monster</l>
               <l>for little boys and girls to wonder at; </l>
               <l>how like a fool I lookt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011946">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> so they do all, </l>
               <l>like great dull slavering fools.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011956">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> Petillius saw too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011963">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> no more of this;  'tis scurvie; peace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011970">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> how nastily, </l>
               <l>indeed how beastly all I did became me?</l>
               <l>How I forgot to blow my nose? There he stands, </l>
               <l>an honest and a wise man; if himself</l>
               <l>(I dare avouch it boldly, for I know it)</l>
               <l>should finde himself in love-</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011992">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I am angry.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000011999">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> surely his wise self would hang his beastly self, </l>
               <l>his understanding self so mawl his asse-self--</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012009">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> he's bound to do it; for he knows the follies, </l>
               <l>the poverties,  and basenesse that belongs to't, </l>
               <l>h'as read upon the reformations long.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012022">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> he has so, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012029">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> 'tis true, and he must do't:</l>
               <l>nor is it fit indeed any such coward -</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012039">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> you'll leave prating.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012046">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> should dare come neer the regiments,  specially</l>
               <l>those curious puppies (for believe there are such)</l>
               <l>that onely love behaviours:those are dog-whelps, </l>
               <l>dwindle away,  because a woman dies well; </l>
               <l>commit with passions onely:fornicate</l>
               <l>with the free spirit meerly:you,  Petillius, </l>
               <l>for you have long observ'd the world.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012071">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> dost thou hear?</l>
               <l>I'll beat thee damnably within these three hours:</l>
               <l>go pray; may be I'll kill thee. Farewel Jack Daws. <stage> Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012087">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> what a strange thing he's grown?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012094">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I am glad he is so:</l>
               <l>and stranger he shall be,  before I leave him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012104">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> is't possible her meer death-----</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012111">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I observ'd him, </l>
               <l>and found him taken,  infinitely taken</l>
               <l>with her bravery:I have follow'd him, </l>
               <l>and seen him kisse his sword since,  court his scabbard, </l>
               <l>call dying,  dainty deer; her brave minde,  mistris; </l>
               <l>casting a thousand ways, to give those forms, </l>
               <l>that he might lie with 'em, and get old armors:</l>
               <l>he had got me o'th'hip once:if shall go hard,  friends, </l>
               <l>but he shall find his own coin.<stage>Enter Macer.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012145">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> how now Macer?<stage>Enter Judas</stage>
               </l>
               <l>is Judas yet come in?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012157">
               <speaker>mac</speaker>
               <l> yes, and has lost</l>
               <l>most of his men too. Here he is.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012167">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> what news?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012174">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> I have lodg'd him; rouze him he that dares.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012181">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> where,  Judas?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012188">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> on a steep rock,  i'th'woods,  the boy too with him, </l>
               <l>and there he swears he will keep his christmas,  gentlemen, </l>
               <l>but he will come away with full conditions, </l>
               <l>bravely,  and like a Britain: he paid part of us, </l>
               <l>yet I think we fought bravely:for mine own part, </l>
               <l>I was four several times at half sword with him, </l>
               <l>twice stood his partizan:but the plain truth is, </l>
               <l>he's a meer devil, and no man:i'th'end he swing'd us, </l>
               <l>and swing'd us soundly too:he fights by with-craft:</l>
               <l>yet for all hat I see him lodg'd, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012222">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> take more men, </l>
               <l>and scout him round. Macer,  march you along.</l>
               <l>What victuals has he?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012235">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> not a piece of bisket, </l>
               <l>not so much as will stop a tooth; nor water, </l>
               <l>more then they make themselves:they lie</l>
               <l>just like a brace of bear-whelps,  close,  and crafty, </l>
               <l>sucking their fingers for their food.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012254">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> cut off then</l>
               <l>all hope of that way:take sufficient forces.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012264">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> but use no foul play,  on your lives:that man</l>
               <l>that does him mischief by deceit, I'll kill him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012274">
               <speaker>Macer</speaker>
               <l> he shall have fair play, he deserves it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012281">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> heark ye, </l>
               <l>what should I do there then? You are brave captains, </l>
               <l>most valiant men; go up your selves; use vertue, </l>
               <l>see what will come on't:pray the gentleman</l>
               <l>to come down, and be taken. Ye all know him, </l>
               <l>I think ye have felt him too:there ye shall find him, </l>
               <l>his sword by his side,  plums of a pound weight by him</l>
               <l>will make your chops ake:you'll finde it a more labour</l>
               <l>to win him living, then climbing of a crowes nest.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012312">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> away, and compasse him; we shall come up</l>
               <l>I am sure within these two hours. Watch him close.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012322">
               <speaker>Macer</speaker>
               <l> he shall flee thorow the air, if he escape us.<stage> a sad noise within.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012332">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> what's this loud lamentation?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012339">
               <speaker>mac</speaker>
               <l> the dead body</l>
               <l>of the great Penyus is new come to th'camp sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012349">
               <speaker>Dem</speaker>
               <l> dead</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012356">
               <speaker>Macer</speaker>
               <l> by himself, they say.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012362">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> I fear'd that fortune.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012369">
               <speaker>Cur</speaker>
               <l> peace guide him up to heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012376">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> away good Macer.  <stage>Exeunt.Macer and Judas.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Swetonius,  Drusus,  Regulus,  Petillius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012389">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> if thou be'st guilty, </l>
               <l>some sullen plague thou hat'st most light upon thee:</l>
               <l>the regiment return on Junius, </l>
               <l>hee well deserves it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012405">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> so.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012412">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> draw out three companies, </l>
               <l>yours Decius,  Junius,  and thou Petillius, </l>
               <l>and make up instantly to Caratach, </l>
               <l>he's in the wood before ye;  we shall follow</l>
               <l>after due ceremony done to the dead, </l>
               <l>the noble dead:come, let's go burn the body.</l>
               <l>  
                  <stage>Exeunt.all but Petillius.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012440">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> the regiment given from me; disgrac'd openly; </l>
               <l>in love too with a trifle to abuse me?</l>
               <l>A merry world,  a fine world: serv'd seven yeers</l>
               <l>to be an asse o'both sides,  sweet Petillius, </l>
               <l>you have brought your hogs to a fine market:you are wise,  sir</l>
               <l>your honourable brain-pan full of crotchets, </l>
               <l>an understanding gentleman; your projects</l>
               <l>cast with assurance ever: wouldst not thou now</l>
               <l>be bang'd about the pate,  Petillius?</l>
               <l>Answer to that sweet souldier;  surely,  surely, </l>
               <l>I think ye would; pull'd by the nose,  kick'd; hang thee, </l>
               <l>thou art the arrant'st rascall:trust thy wisdome</l>
               <l>with any thing of weight; the winde with feathers.</l>
               <l>Out ye blind puppie; you command? You govern?</l>
               <l>Dig for a groat a day, or serve a swine-herd; </l>
               <l>too noble for thy nature too. I must up; </l>
               <l>but what I shall do there,  let time discover. <stage> exit</stage>
               </l>  
            </sp>
            </div>
            <div xmlns:seasr="http://www.seasr.org/ns/services/openmary/tei/1.0"
              seasr:sid="400000012500">
               <head> Scaena Tertia.</head>
            <stage>Enter Macer and Judas,  with meat and a bottle.</stage>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012507">
               <speaker>mac</speaker>
               <l> hang it o'th'side o'th'rock, as though the Britains</l>
               <l>stole hither to relieve him; who first ventures</l>
               <l>to fetch it off,  is ours. I cannot see him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012520">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> he lies close in a hole above,  I know it, </l>
               <l>gnawing upon his anger: ha? No,  'tis not he, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012530">
               <speaker>Macer</speaker> 
               <l>'tis but the shaking of the boughs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012537">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> ---shake 'em, </l>
               <l>I am sure they shake me soundly. There.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012547">
               <speaker>Macer</speaker>
               <l> 'tis nothing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012554">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> make no noise: if he stir, a deadly tempest</l>
               <l>of huge stones fall upon us:'tis done:away close. <stage> exit</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Caratach.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012569">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> sleep stil,  sleep sweetly child,  'tis all thou feedst on.</l>
               <l>No gentle Britain neer;  no valiant charitie</l>
               <l>to bring thee food?poor knave, thou art sick, extreme sick, </l>
               <l>almost grown wild for meat; and yet thy goodnesse</l>
               <l>will not confesse,  nor show it. All the woods</l>
               <l>are double lin'd with souldiers; no way left us</l>
               <l>to make a noble scape:I'll sit down by thee, </l>
               <l>and when thou wak'st, either get meat to save thee, </l>
               <l>or lose my life i'th' purchase. Good gods comfort thee.<stage>Enter Junius,  Decius,  Petillius,  guide.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012603">
               <speaker>guide</speaker>
               <l> ye are not far off now, sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012610">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> draw the companies</l>
               <l>the closest way thorow the woods; we'll keep on this way.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012620">
               <speaker>guide</speaker>
               <l> I will sir:half a furlong more you'll come</l>
               <l>within the sight o'th'rock; keep on the left side, </l>
               <l>you'll be discoverd else:I'll lodge your companies</l>
               <l>in the wilde vines beyond ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012636">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> do ye mark him?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012643">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> yes,  and am sorry for him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012650">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> Junius, </l>
               <l>pray let me speak two words with you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012660">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> walk afore, </l>
               <l>I'll overtake ye straight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012670">
               <speaker>Dec</speaker>
               <l> I will. <stage> Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012680">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> now,  captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012687">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> you have oft told me you have lov'd me, Junius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012694">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> most sure I told you truth then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012701">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> and that love</l>
               <l>should not deny me any honest thing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012711">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> it shall not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012718">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> dare ye swear it?</l>
               <l>I have forgot all passages between us</l>
               <l>that have been ill, forgiven too,  forgot you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012731">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> what would this man have? By---I do,  sir, </l>
               <l>so it be fit to grant ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012741">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> 'tis most honest.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012748">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> why, then I'll do it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012755">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> kill mee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012762">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> how?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012769">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> pray kill me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012776">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> kill ye?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012783">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> i,  kill me quickly,  suddenly, </l>
               <l>now kill me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012793">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> on what reason? Ye amaze me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012800">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> if ye do love me, kill me, ask me not why:</l>
               <l>I would be kill'd, and by you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012810">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> mercy on me, </l>
               <l>what ails this man? Petillius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012820">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> pray ye dispatch me, </l>
               <l>ye are not safe whilest I live:I am dangerous, </l>
               <l>troubled extremely,  even to mischief,  Junius, </l>
               <l>an enemie to all good men: fear not,  'tis justice; </l>
               <l>I shall kill you else.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012839">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> tell me but the cause, </l>
               <l>and I will do it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012849">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I am disgrac'd,  my service</l>
               <l>slighted,  and unrewarded by the generall, </l>
               <l>my hopes left wilde and naked; besides these, </l>
               <l>I am grown ridiculous,  an asse,  a folly</l>
               <l>I dare not trust my self with:prethee kill me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012868">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> all these may be redeem'd as easily</l>
               <l>as you would heal your finger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012878">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> nay--</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012885">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> stay, I'll do it, </l>
               <l>you shall not need your anger:but first,  Petillius, </l>
               <l>you shall unarm your self; I dare not trust</l>
               <l>a man so bent to mischief.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012901">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> there's my sword; </l>
               <l>and do it handsomely.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012911">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> yes, I will kill ye, </l>
               <l>beleeve that certaine:but first I'll lay before ye</l>
               <l>the most extreme fool ye have plaid in this, </l>
               <l>the honour purpos'd for ye, the great honour</l>
               <l>the generall intended ye, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012930">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> how?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012937">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> and then I'll kill ye, </l>
               <l>because ye shall die miserable. Know sir, </l>
               <l>the regiment was given me,  but till time</l>
               <l>call'd ye to do some worthie deed might stop</l>
               <l>the peoples ill thoughts of ye for lord Penyus, </l>
               <l>I mean his death. How soon this time's come to ye, </l>
               <l>and hasted by Swetonius? Go,  sayes he, </l>
               <l>Junius and Decius,  and go thou Petillius; </l>
               <l>distinctly, thou Petillius,  and draw up, </l>
               <l>to take stout Caratach:there's the deed purpos'd, </l>
               <l>a deed to take off all faults, of all natures:</l>
               <l>and thou Petillius; mark it, there's the honour, </l>
               <l>and that done,  all made even.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012980">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> stay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000012987">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> no, I'll kill ye.</l>
               <l>He knew thee absolute, and full in souldier, </l>
               <l>daring beyond all dangers,  found thee out</l>
               <l>according to the boldnesse of thy spirit, </l>
               <l>a subject,  such a subject.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013006">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> heark ye Junius, </l>
               <l>I will live now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013016">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> by no means. Wooed thy worth, </l>
               <l>held thee by the chin up, as thou sankst,  and shew'd thee</l>
               <l>how honour held her arms out:come, make ready, </l>
               <l>since ye will die an asse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013032">
               <speaker>petil</speaker>
               <l> thou wilt not kill me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013039">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> by-----but I will sir:I'll have no man dangerous</l>
               <l>live to destroy me afterward. Besides,  you have gotten</l>
               <l>honour enough, let young men rise now. Nay, </l>
               <l>I do preceive too by the generall,  (which</l>
               <l>is one main cause ye shall die) how ere he carry it, </l>
               <l>such a strong doting on ye,  that I fear, </l>
               <l>you shall command in chief:how are we paid then?</l>
               <l>Come,  if you will pray, dispatch it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013067">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> is there no way?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013074">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> not any way to live.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013081">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> I will do any thing, </l>
               <l>redeem my self at any price:good Junius, </l>
               <l>let me but die upon the rock,  but offer</l>
               <l>my life up like a souldier.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013097">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> you will seek then</l>
               <l>to out-doe every man.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013107">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> beleeve it Junius, </l>
               <l>you shall goe stroak by stroak with me, </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013117">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> you'll leave off too, </l>
               <l>as you are noble,  and a souldier, </l>
               <l>for ever these mad fancies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013130">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> dare ye trust me?</l>
               <l>By all that's good and honest.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013140">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> there's your sword then, </l>
               <l>and now come on a new man: vertue guide thee.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Caratach and Hengo on the rock.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013156">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> courage my boy, I have found meat:look Hengo, </l>
               <l>look where some blessed Britain, to preserve thee, </l>
               <l>has hung a little food and drink:cheer up boy, </l>
               <l>do not forsake me now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013172">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> o uncle,  uncle, </l>
               <l>I feel I cannot stay long:yet I'll fetch it, </l>
               <l>to keep your noble life: uncle,  I am heart whole, </l>
               <l>and would live.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013188">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thou shalt, long I hope.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013195">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> but my head,  uncle:</l>
               <l>me thinks the rock goes round. <stage>Enter Macer and jud.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013208">
               <speaker>Macer</speaker>
               <l> mark 'em well,  Judas.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013215">
               <speaker>Jud</speaker>
               <l> peace,  as you love your life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013222">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> do not you hear</l>
               <l>the noise of bels?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013232">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> of bels boy? 'Tis thy fancie, </l>
               <l>alas,  thy bodie's full of wind.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013242">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> me thinks sir, </l>
               <l>they ring a strange sad knell, a preparation</l>
               <l>to some neer funerall of state:nay, weep not, </l>
               <l>mine owne sweet uncle, you will kill me sooner.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013258">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> o my poor chicken.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013265">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> fie,  faint-hearted uncle:</l>
               <l>come,  tie me in your belt, and let me down.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013275">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I'll go my self, boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013282">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> no, as ye love mee,  uncle; </l>
               <l>I will not eat it,  if I doe not fetch it; </l>
               <l>the danger onely I desire:pray tie me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013295">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I will, and all my care hang ore thee:come child, </l>
               <l>my valiant child.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013305">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> let me down apace,  uncle, </l>
               <l>and ye shall see how like a daw I'll whip it</l>
               <l>from all their policies:for 'tis most certain</l>
               <l>a Roman train:and ye must hold me sure too, </l>
               <l>you'll spoil all else. When I have brought it uncle, </l>
               <l>wee'll be as merry--</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013327">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> go i'th'name of heaven boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013334">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> quick,  quick,  uncle, I have it. Oh.<stage> Judas shoots Hengo.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013344">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> what ailest thou?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013351">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> o my best uncle,  I am slain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013358">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I see yee,  and heaven direct my hand:destruction<stage> Caratach kils Judas with a stone from the rock</stage>
               </l>
               <l>go with thy coward soul. How dost thou boy?</l>
               <l>Oh villain,  pocky villain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013373">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> o uncle,  uncle, </l>
               <l>oh how it pricks mee:am I preserv'd for this?</l>
               <l>Extremely pricks me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013386">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> coward,  rascall coward, </l>
               <l>dogs eat thy flesh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013396">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> oh I bleed hard:I faint too,  out upon't, </l>
               <l>how sick I am? The lean rogue,  uncle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013406">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> look boy, </l>
               <l>I have laid him sure enough.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013416">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> have ye knockt his brains out?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013422">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I warrant thee for stirring more:cheer up,  child.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013429">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> hold my sides hard,  stop,  stop,  oh wretched fortune, </l>
               <l>must we part thus? Still I grow sicker,  uncle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013439">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> heaven look upon this noble child.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013446">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> I once hop'd</l>
               <l>I should have liv'd to have met these bloody Romans</l>
               <l>at my swords point, to have reveng'd my father, </l>
               <l>to have beaten 'em: oh hold me hard. But uncle--</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013462">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> thou shalt live still I hope boy. Shall I draw it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013469">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> ye draw away my soul then. I would live</l>
               <l>a little longer; spare me heavens,  but onely</l>
               <l>to thank you for your tender love. Good uncle, </l>
               <l>good noble uncle weep not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013485">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> oh my chicken, </l>
               <l>my deer boy,  what shall I lose?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013495">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> why,  a child, </l>
               <l>that must have died how-ever; had this scap'd me, </l>
               <l>feaver or famine:I was born to die,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013507">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> but thus unblown, my boy?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013514">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> I goe the straighter</l>
               <l>my journey to the gods: sure I shall know ye</l>
               <l>when ye come,  uncle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013527">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> yes,  boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013534">
               <speaker>Hen</speaker>
               <l> and I hope</l>
               <l>wee shall enjoy together that great blessednesse</l>
               <l>you told me of.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013547">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> most certain,  child.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013554">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> I grow cold, </l>
               <l>mine eyes are going.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013564">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> lift 'em up.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013571">
               <speaker>Hengo</speaker>
               <l> pray for me; </l>
               <l>and noble uncle,  when my bones are ashes, </l>
               <l>think of your little nephew. Mercie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013584">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> mercie.</l>
               <l>You blessed angels take him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013594">
               <speaker>Heng</speaker>
               <l> kisse me:so.</l>
               <l>Farewell,  farewell. <stage> dies.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013607">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> farewell the hopes of Britain, </l>
               <l>thou royall graft,  farewell for ever. Time and death, </l>
               <l>ye have done your worst. Fortune now see,  now proudly</l>
               <l>pluck off thy vail, and view thy triumph:look, </l>
               <l>look what thou hast brought this land to. Oh fair flower, </l>
               <l>how lovely yet thy ruines show,  how sweetly</l>
               <l>even death embraces thee the peace of heaven, </l>
               <l>the fellowship of all great souls be with thee.<stage>Enter Petillius and Junius on the rock</stage>
               </l>
               <l>hah? Dare ye Romans? Ye shall win me bravely.</l>
               <l>Thou art mine. <stage> fight.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013646">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> not yet,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013653">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l>breathe ye,  ye poor Romans, </l>
               <l>and come up all,  with all your ancient valours, </l>
               <l>like a rough winde I'll shake your souls,  and send 'em--<stage>Enter Swetonius,  and all the Roman captains.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013669">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> yeeld thee bold Caratach;  by all-----</l>
               <l>as I am souldier,  as I envie thee, </l>
               <l>I'll use thee like thy self, the valiant Britain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013682">
               <speaker>Pet</speaker>
               <l> brave soldier yeeld; thou stock of arms and honor, </l>
               <l>thou filler of the world with fame and glory.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013692">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> most worthy man,  we'l woo thee,  be thy prisoners.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013699">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> excellent Britain, do me but that honour, </l>
               <l>that more to me then conquests,  that true happinesse, </l>
               <l>to be my friend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013712">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> o Romans,  see what here is:</l>
               <l>had this boy liv'd---</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013722">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> for fames sake,  for thy swords sake, </l>
               <l>as thou desirest to build thy vertues greater:</l>
               <l>by all that's excellent in man,  and honest--</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013735">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I do beleeve: ye have had me a brave foe; </l>
               <l>make we a noble friend,  and from your goodnesse, </l>
               <l>give this boy honourable earth to lie in.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013748">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> he shall have fitting funerall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013755">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> I yeeld then, </l>
               <l>not to your blowes, but your brave courtesies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013765">
               <speaker>Petill</speaker>
               <l> thus we conduct then to the arms of peace</l>
               <l>the wonder of the world.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013775">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> thus I embrace thee,  <stage> flourish</stage>
               </l>
               <l>and let it be no flattery that I tell thee, </l>
               <l>thou art the onely souldier.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013790">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> how to thank ye</l>
               <l>I must hereafter finde upon your usage.</l>
               <l>I am for Rome?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013803">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> ye must.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013810">
               <speaker>Car</speaker>
               <l> then Rome shall know</l>
               <l>the man that makes her spring of glory grow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013820">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> Petillius,  you have shown much worth this day, </l>
               <l>redeem'd much errour, </l>
               <l>ye have my love again,  preserve it. Junius, </l>
               <l>with you I make him equall in the regiment.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013836">
               <speaker>Jun</speaker>
               <l> the elder and the nobler. I'll give place,  sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp seasr:id="500000013843">
               <speaker>Swet</speaker>
               <l> ye shew a friends soul.</l>
               <l> March on, and through the camp in every tongue.</l>
               <l>The vertues of great Caratach be sung.  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            </div>
      
      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
